All who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him,
and they will praise and bless and celebrate with song the Lord of Spirits.
1st denoc, chapter 48, verses 4 through 5.
The modern world doesn't acknowledge but is nevertheless haunted by spirits,
angels, demons, and saints.
In our time, many year into break free of the prison of a flat, secular materialism,
to see and to know reality as it truly is.
What is this?
spiritual reality like. How do we engage with it well? How do we permeate every day life with
spiritual presence? Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick, and Father Stephen
De Young, host this live Colin show focused on enchantment in creation, the union of the scene
and unseen as made by God and experienced by mankind throughout history. Welcome to the Lord of
Good evening, giant killers, dragon slayers, serpent stone.
You are listening to Lord of Spheres podcast.
My co-host Father Stephen DeYoung is with me from Lafayette, Louisiana.
And I'm Father Andrew Stephen Damick in Emmaus, Pennsylvania.
This is not a live broadcast.
It's not a memory, either.
But it is nonetheless pre-recorded because when this episode releases,
I will be a cross on ocean from where I normally am.
No, I was going to say.
I mean, technically you're always a cross on ocean.
That's true.
But from where I'm all relative.
Yes. Yes. So many oceans to choose from really. Yeah. So tonight everybody, we have a hot
one. There's probably no subject more subject to pop theology than damnation. Some of you
out there were raised with the idea that everyone is born going to hell. Sometimes it's
that good people go to heaven forever when they die, but bad people go to hell forever when
They die.
Sometimes it's a little more complex than that with some religious involvement being
key to heaven forever.
Some people think that hell is a temporary problem, with forever heaven being everyone's
eventual fate.
Yet the scriptures speak of eternal condemnation, and there is also the resurrection of the
body, which is a key Christian dog bone.
So what is eternal condemnation?
are the biblical images, is universalism and acceptable orthodox.
view. It's a hot and spicy episode tonight. So, Father Stephen, isn't it true that with really core
questions like the nature of demination, that there are a range of acceptable Orthodox views and we
could just pick the one that we like best? No. Good night, everybody. Haven't done one of those
in a while. Yeah, I think, you know, I read your little intro thing and I think I got the wrong idea
because I have like this
tray of successively spicier hot wings in front of me. I thought we were doing that.
Oh, when you said it was a hot one. So you're going to, like, as we go, you're going to taste
another wing. And that's, that was where I thought we were going. But I'm, I'm thinking
maybe I read that wrong. An animated gif of Shaquille O'Neill, tasting a spicy hot wing.
But yeah, the idea, I mean we'll get it this more later on.
Obviously, but orthodoxia, right?
Right or correct opinion or viewpoint or perspective.
You can't have multiple ones.
Yeah, it's not like the details of,
should you wear high back or low back vestments, right?
Where there's variation.
It's not a matter of orthodoxy.
Right, right.
Right, that distinction, right?
Like, you could have an infinite number of heterodoxies
like by definition, it could be an infinite number
of other opinions that are incorrect
to varying degrees, but you can't have
like these two or three conflicting opinions
are all correct.
Right, right.
I mean, basic logic.
There can be, as we've pointed out many times,
can be variation in the
language, you know, like, is man body and soul or is he body, soul and spirit? Well, those
are different ways of talking about essentially the same thing. But that's not, that's not
what we're talking about here. Yes. But if there is genuine disagreement, where there
is genuine disagreement, you could both be wrong. You can't both be right, right? Equally
and in the same sense. Yes, this is how yeah, this is just very, very basic logic.
Yes, and this is actually a good way to set the tone for this episode because
One of the themes tonight is gonna be
This isn't really hard
This isn't really a hard question
This is really simple you could read scripture you could read the father you could read our hymns
like
There is no real ambiguity here.
No, there's no real complexity here.
Yeah, especially like the heonography.
I mean, you really have to work at it
to get some kind of ambiguity out of it.
And that's it.
The waters have been muddied by people for various reasons.
Yeah.
This has been made confusing by certain modern theologians
Deliberate.
not because it's really unclear, but because they don't like what is clear.
And so things get muddied, people get confused.
There are other ambiguities that aren't sort of a result of that kind of deliberate problematizing,
right?
There are some that are just a result of a long history of sort of pop theology, right?
as you mentioned.
And...
over simplifications and that kind of thing.
So there are some things that we're going to be disambiguating that are of that nature.
Yeah.
And that's basically where we're going to start because like this idea of going to
hell when you die, which is sort of the idea of damnation that a lot of people have
in their heads is actually not Christian teaching, not really.
Right.
You know.
Christianity does not teach.
where bad people go and they die,
is that they go to a lake of fire and fry.
Wow, that rhymed, very nice.
Yes, well, it might have been a reference to something.
It also had a little bit of a iteration,
so I really appreciated it.
Yeah.
Yeah, so yeah, and what we're trying to do with this episode,
what we're trying to do in this episode is not sort of,
because I'm anti-
dissipating certain things.
Right.
Let's just set the matter to the beginning.
We're gonna be criticized for our tone.
Yeah.
We're gonna be called condescending and flippant.
We're gonna get the very glib mat, very glib.
And we're...
Warning, this podcast includes sarcasm.
Yeah.
It's so lame because I know exactly already in advance no matter what we do.
We're going to get accused that we're teaching our own opinion as if it was the
teaching of the Orthodox Church because we're going to disambiguate the teaching of the Orthodox
Church and some people aren't going to like it. And therefore they're going to say,
Well, that's not the teacher of the orthodox church.
It's just like your opinion, man.
which it isn't. I caught that reference. Right. There are these things, there are these
things we're going to get. There's, there's going to be appeals to authority with smart people
who disagree with this because we're going to be, the way we're going to present it,
get called, there's a trigger warning. Like I said, our goal here is to present the apostolic
like teaching all this.
And so we see people who disagree with that is disagreeing with the apostolic teaching.
And so we're going to get, yeah, well, so and so disagrees and he's really smart.
You know, whatever those are those are the things.
Just say events we're going to get.
And it's not actually going to be with reference, any argument we would make or any data we
present or any material we present.
all those things.
are just based on disagreement.
Yeah, I mean, there are some substantial disagreements
that could be made, and we're gonna talk about some
of that stuff as we go.
Yeah, but, yeah.
But if you want me to do anything that just kind of like
chuckle and treat it as a trophy,
your virulent criticism of this episode,
you need to actually respond to the content.
There we go.
not just take shots.
me or talk about how much smarter your guy is in your mind. So yeah. So the first big disambiguation
we need to make is between Hades and hell sort of. Yeah. Like on the one hand, these are synonyms
in the sense that they both, that like Hades comes out of Greek and hell...
comes out of the Germanic languages and both refer in those pagan contexts to a place,
the underworld, where people go and they die, especially in a pre-Christian sense.
In that sense, they are synonyms.
Of course, it's why Hell is used in the King James Bible because that is the traditional
word for the
underworld in Germanic languages like English.
You know, right. Right.
But in modern English parlons,
hell is used to refer to where bad folks go when they die.
It's used to refer also to the place where
The Devil and Demon
and bad folks go after the last judgment. And those two things, you by using the same term,
get sort of smushed together, then you get your, your added, Miltonian notions of the devil being
like the ruler of hell.
Yeah, which is, I mean, is frankly kind of big.
right instead of being confined there, right? So yeah, look at the transition. If anybody
still doubts me on this Milton thing, look at the difference between the devil in hell in
Milton as romantic figure who'd rather rule in hell than serve in heaven and the devil
in Dante.
Hmm. Yeah, right. Right? Who's the prisoner in the deepest pit? Yeah, there's not a lot
time between those two texts.
in the grand scheme of things.
Yeah.
But there's a definite transition there, the way that Devils viewed.
And it just kind of the popular Christian world, at least in the United States, the Miltonian
view is the one that has sort of taken over, despite it's sort of a historicity of the
fact that it's not really reflected in the Bible.
say either. So, um, Hades, right, Hades. And we talked about this, um, in terms of the
cosmic geography of the underworld in, uh, I think that was the, that's what we talked
about in down to Hades.
Down to Hades, a Catholic, a Catholic.
I'm never sure how pronounced that word cathonic
Odyssey. Yeah, that's sort of like the geography of the underworld.
Right. Yeah. So we talked about the underworld as place with place and scare quotes, right?
Because of course, what do we mean by place? We don't mean like an extension of physical
space that you could measure, right? Like we've gone through this before that this is
spatial terms and temporal terms being used sort of
analogically, right? Because of course
the underworld is full of at least relative to us humans bodyless beings.
That therefore don't have extension in space per se.
We also talked about this a fair amount in our Lord of Spirits goes to hell episode
where we talked about the harrowing of Hades. We sort of revisited it
and some of those.
places. And so when you look at all of the hemnography surrounding Posca, for example,
yes, not one dead remains in the tomb. For instance, right. All the harrowing of Hades language,
this is talking about Hades. Yep. Right. This is talking about the place where everyone went
that way that when they died.
before Christ's harrowing of Hades.
And in those episodes, we're not going to go all through to get in detail because we're
doing this to disambiguate.
This episode is not about Hades, right?
But remember, for example, that was sort of schematized in the book of Enoch that there
were these sort of four caves, right?
One K was the martyrs and one was the righteous one was the ignorant.
one was the wicked, right? And the righteous dead sort of had a spring of water in their cave.
And that's kind of reflected in the background of the parable of the rich man and Lazarus.
Yeah, right. Where Lazarus is in this place that's very bad, or the rich man is in places very bad,
Lazarus is in Abraham's bosom. He's with Abraham and
the rich man asks for water that sort of implies that there's some kind of water where Lazarus is
and not where he is, right? So and then the idea, of course, the Harry Haydes, you could go back to
that episode for all the details is Christa Sands and brings the righteous and the martyrs to
of paradise.
Right.
And so, right, like, Hades gets cleared out.
Yeah, but only of the righteous.
Like the wicked and the angels who left their former estate,
they are still changed there as St. Peter mentions,
post-resurrection in his puzzle.
Right, and part of the no body,
remains in the grave, right? Keep in mind, there's nothing in the gospels at least to say that
everyone was physically resurrected at that time. No. Right. I know that's the funny thing is,
I've seen some people interpret this as, I mean, we'll get more into this, but as essentially that,
you know, everybody is saved to whatever based on the
But it's like, well, that's the herring of Hades.
And it does mention that a bunch of people came out of their tombs for a while.
But not everybody.
And it says it was the saints.
It was.
Yeah, it was only for a while.
Yeah, it wasn't everybody.
And those people all died again.
They were since you resuscitated.
They weren't really resurrected in the truest sense.
Right.
And that's because what that Possible Hymnography is trying to convey in addition to the
Very good.
of Hades is what we talked about last time about Christ being the first born from the dead
and the first fruits of the resurrection.
Yeah.
There will be a general resurrection and POSCA participates in that.
Right.
Is the beginning of it.
Yeah.
Right.
Is the down payment on it.
This Christ resurrection, the sign of it.
So right, you have that going on, but the problem you just mentioned of how people interpret
that.
part because of the idea that heller Hades has been sort of equated with the place of
ultimate condemnation after the last judgment.
Yeah.
And these are two different things.
Yep.
Right.
So we've done a couple episodes talking about Hades.
Today's episode is not about Hades.
You can also talk about Hades.
That sort of Hades as in scare quotes place.
also.
hate is a sort of experience, right?
After people die.
And we've talked about this in terms of what's called the intermediate state.
And the reason it's called the intermediate state,
what you're talking about it theologically, is that it's the state of a human soul
between their physical death and their bodily response.
direction. Yeah, we believe in a two-stage eschatology, as it's sometimes called, like there
is an eschatology of what happens to you immediately when you die, and then there's an eschatology
of the general resurrection and what happens after that, as long as we're talking on linear
temporal terms. Right. And there is a way in which then paradise and
and Hades are used as terms to describe...
that state for different people. For some people that state is described as paradise,
right? Being in the presence of God, being with Christ, being in Christ, right? The dead in Christ,
our life being hidden in Christ, and then on the other side as Hades,
right? As some kind of negative state, right? But paradise and Hades as an experience or as a state
in which the
soul is and we've talked before to show about all the problems of how exactly we could imagine
that as embodied beings.
Yeah.
Not just accidentally embodied beings, but by nature embodied beings, right?
What that state is like and how what experiences things like time and space when one is no
longer embodied.
That's not something we could really conceive of.
So we use MetaF
But we don't mean that like your force goes to sitting around
Somewhere for years and years and years and years and years waiting for Christ's return
right
That's why I keep using the language of state right state of being state of existence right because it's the best sort of vague way
Right to not
to help prevent us from over-literalizing things in this regard.
It's really it is even over-literalizing.
It's over-materializing, right?
Thank you of them in material terms.
This is a problem too, by the way.
And I know because I saw a little bit of feedback on our last episode where we talked about
the ascension that literal and material are not synonyms.
Yeah.
Right, like, scientific...
material reality and literal do not mean the same thing. There are lots of
things that are literally true that are not statements of scientific materialism.
Yeah, so all the things that scripture says about the intermediate state, about
paradise and Hades and other experience by people after the death of the body are
are all literally true.
But none of them are scientific material statements.
Right.
Those aren't the same thing.
And we've talked a little about how in the past, about how this relates to the idea of
praying for the departed.
And I know this has been a sticking point for a lot of people too.
So.
So we'll spend a little time with it here and hopefully this will help sort of disambiguate.
Right.
So what we've said before in a couple of different contexts is following St. John of
Damascus that are bodily life in this material world, right, in the present age, right, is
is given to us for...
We have mortal bodies so that we can repent.
And so beings without mortal bodies,
and jellic beings, however we want, whatever label we want to use for them,
whether they're fallen or unfallen,
and humans who have died physically, meaning their souls were separated from their body.
Right.
Um, is there for not, they're not embodying?
at that in that state are not able to repent.
And so repentance is sort of confined to this life.
And I know this is a hard thing to get your brain around.
And I think part of the reason why people have trouble
getting their brain around what St. John is saying
is the bad way we've been taught
to think about what repentance is.
Yeah, we tend to think of it as how you feel.
Really, I mean, that's really what it comes down to is.
I mean, we've all heard this in confession.
People saying, I know I'm supposed to forgive,
but I just can't forgive him.
I just can't forgive her.
And by that, they don't mean I can't take
the 3D world actions not to take revenge to be reconciled.
They mean I don't I can't imagine the
I will feel any differently about this.
Right.
There's not a wand I can wave
where I don't feel hurting upset.
Right.
And it's like yes, you are right.
There is no such thing.
For forgiveness is not the opposite
of feeling hurt and upset.
Yes.
And I'll just go ahead.
This is my want.
So
part of what's happened in our society. And this actually started in evangelical Christianity and
is spread outward to the rest of, again, this is where I live. So I have to mainly speak about
American culture. But since we export our American culture imperialistically to the rest of the
the world, it's probably true a lot of other places too.
We've obviously one of the things we've talked about a lot is the difference between the
contemporary idea or even the historic Protestant idea of faith and the idea of faithfulness.
And how that concept of faith is the direct result of having sort of, of having set up a
dichotomy
between it and works.
Yeah, right.
So when you set up an economy,
you can't set up an economy
between faithfulness and works, right?
Like it doesn't work, pardon the pun.
But when you set up that economy,
when you remove works from faith,
so that faith is a thing
and then works is another thing
that is somehow related to it.
And then you can argue about how they're related,
but it's a separate thing.
then essentially what what faith becomes is intellectual ascent plus feelings
Plus feelings of love loyalty whatever right
That grow out of that intellectual as
Even gelical Christianity at least here in the United States has evolved
over time.
I'm slowly but surely, the actual content of faith, meaning the propositions to which you
have to give intellectual ascent have dwindled down and dwindled down and dwindled down and
dwindled down.
You look at like a historic Calvinist or Lutheran or even Methodist church and Oldsburg
that research.
There are a whole list of things that you have to sign on for, right, that you have to give your
intellectual ascent to in their minds, right? But those have dwindled down and down now to the point
where a lot of non-enominational evangelical churches, it's like you have to believe in Jesus.
Yeah. And then he died for you. And beyond that, even who
Jesus was or is and what it means that he died for you and how that worked are up for
grabs.
Right?
So, what happens when you take away, when you have something that's a combination of
intellectual ascent and feelings, right?
Essentially.
And you take away the propositions to which you have to ascent is your mainly left with
feelings.
Right.
And so faith primarily becomes about these sort of feelings of attachment.
And that's been opposed to works.
And this plays out in all of these places in society.
I've talked before like all the woke stuff that people get so mad about online is just
atheistic Protestantism.
It's just...
I need to
publicly given by a scent to certain propositions that Merrick me out is a good person.
Yeah, then you're right.
One of the elect.
Yeah.
But one of the ways, one of the ways, one of the horrible ways this has actually worked out
in our modern society with the feelings thing is empathy.
Yes, Father Steve Adiog is
now going to speak against empathy.
I don't think anyone who knows you would be shocked about this.
Well, this is true, but empathy is mostly worthless.
Okay.
The person who comes to you and needs food doesn't care if you feel his pain.
Hmm.
He doesn't actually want you to sit next to him and be with him in his suffering.
Right? He was?
you to give them food. Yeah, I think most of the people who want the empathy, their lives,
in terms of like their needs and their suffering, their lives are probably pretty good.
Most of the time. Yes. Actually doing things has value.
Thoughts and prayers, tweets that you're thinking of someone, don't help them.
Thank you.
Helping them helps them.
Calling them and spending time talking to them
if that's what they need.
Again, actually doing it helps them.
Not just having general good feelings toward them.
Right?
And so repentance likewise has been
sort of reduced to feeling.
Well, I feel really bad about it.
That's repentance.
Yeah, no, it needs to be changed.
you gotta make change.
Yes, and our definition of an unrepentant sinner now is someone who doesn't feel bad about it.
Hmm. Yeah.
Right. And Gaulan is actually doing anything.
Right. And I think one of the...
And people hijacked stuff from the scripture to kind of back this up.
For instance, there's the scripture language about doing things with your whole heart.
It doesn't mean that you feel it really big.
No.
That means that if someone observed you,
they could see, oh yes, he's really doing it.
You know, like you're doing it intentionally.
Yeah, like if someone's digging a ditch half-heartedly,
that means they're barely digging.
Yes.
If I walk by someone and happen to drop my water bottle,
that's not the same as giving them water.
Right.
Right, you have to do it intentionally.
Yeah.
Right.
But so yeah.
And so repentance is not just about you feeling guilty.
It's not about, it's definitely not you feeling bad
about the consequences of your actions
and wanting to get out of them.
But then you have this whole,
and this is destructive in the case of repentance
because
people get lost in this sort of psychoanalytic maze.
Right of, oh am I really repentant? I don't know. Am I? Is it just because of the consequence?
Yeah. Am I trying to? Do I really feel bad about it? Do I feel bad enough about it?
Right. And then they often think, wow, you know, I'm I'm I'm in danger of hellfire.
I really need a related episode because I don't feel all the right things
I, you know, as a really interesting anecdote.
So, you know, I don't know that I've mentioned on this show, but like one of the projects
that I'm working on is a documentary on related to my pilgrimage to Lithuania called The Wolf
and the Cross.
A couple episodes out, everybody listen to it.
But one of the things that we'll show up in episode three, which as of now has not been
released yet, is a poem written by St. Athanasius of Breast when he was thrown into prison by
the unites.
And a friend of mine who's in Lithuania not only dug this up but translated it for me from
what's called old-chanceuryslvanic.
And if you read it, like there's parts where he's sort of blessing his enemies and then
there's parts where he's super mad at his enemies and like condemning them.
And you know, you read it, it's like, okay, this is a guy who has all kinds of feelings.
Yeah, beautiful and kind.
and tender others are really like he's not doing well.
He seems to be pretty depressed,
but it's clear that he's a saint.
It's not just because they shot him in the head
and dumped him in the ground
when he didn't die buried alive,
although that did happen.
But you know, saints had,
or saint David right in the Psalms.
There's some pretty serious depressed feelings
going on in some of the Psalms.
It doesn't mean he's not repenting.
Right.
Feelings are epiphenomenal.
They have value only if they're related to your actions.
Yeah.
Yeah, without actions are valueless, right?
Someone in your community has a spouse pass away, right?
You sitting in your house and feeling bad for them does nothing for them.
You making some food and bringing it to their house does something for them.
You actually doing something for them, right?
And you doing that for them.
going over there with the food and eating the food with them.
There will be feelings and emotions
that will come along with that and that you'll share,
but those will be valuable
because they're accompanying what you're actually doing.
Yeah, right.
They aren't valuable just sort of in abstraction
in and of themselves, right?
So on the one side, yeah,
repentance is not about how you feel.
So
When we say that demons can't repent, we don't mean demons can't be like, man, this stinks.
I'm going to be confined to a lake of fire for all eternity.
Maybe I should change my mind.
We don't know what it's like to be a demon.
Yeah, but I mean, there's the scene right in first enich where the watchers are like, hey
God likes you.
You go put it a good word for us.
Maybe get us out of this punishment a little early.
Right?
That's not repentance.
No, and even the rich man and Lazarus,
there's not any repentance in any of the things he says.
He just doesn't like to suffer.
Yeah.
He's just like, yeah, I don't like this suffering.
Hey, I like my family enough that, you know,
I don't particularly want them to suffer like this.
But that's not repentance.
Right?
Right? That's not repentance. So we're not saying that somehow being outside the body
means you can't have certain feelings or think certain thoughts. Of course you can't.
That's not repentance, though. Yeah. Yeah. That's not repentance, though. Yeah. And it's
It's also not about making God not mad at you.
Repentance is not something you do.
and this is more maybe from another perspective. This may come, well, this is another thread in Western theology.
Let's just say, because there's various Western groups that are more on this side, where it's, you have sinned, you have broken one of God's rules, right?
Right. Therefore he's quite irate. And right, you're, he's going to send you to hell
unless you do whatever.
is required, right? Usually involving asking, just asking for forgiveness, but sometimes doing
that in a context, right? Then if you do that, then you're off the hook, right? God's
not mad at you anymore. That also is not repentance. There is nothing that we do in the church
that changes God.
Yeah, or in the somewhat amusing to me, but really on point words of
Metropolitan Erotheos Vlacos, God does not need therapy.
Yeah, he does that need to change.
And doesn't and isn't going to. So that's.
So the, the, this is the difference between
and prayer on one hand and
magic on the other. Right? We aren't trying to change God. God doesn't need to change.
The father and the parable of the prodigal son always loves his son and is always waiting
for him to come home. Even though disrespected by his son pretty abominably and abandoned,
etc. He never gets angry at his son.
and throws them out or puts some barrier in the way of him coming back.
Yeah.
Right.
So this has nothing to do with repentance, has nothing to do with changing God.
Repentance is about when you sin, you do damage to yourself and to other people and
to the world around you.
And repentance is you doing everything you can to repair the damage.
damage you've done and to heal it, both yourself to other people and to the world around
you. That's what repentance is. That kind of requires a body. Yeah, because you have to
do stuff. You have to do stuff. Right. And demons can't directly do stuff in the world.
and humans after the
the physical death can't directly do stuff in the world.
Yep. Yep. They can't not only can they not roll back the
clock and not do the things they did, right? They can't go
and apologize. They can't make amends. They can't anymore,
right? They can't make restitution anymore. That's why we say
repentance isn't possible because of what repentance really is
And so as we've mentioned before in terms of prayers for the departed, they're not able to repent.
And so in a sense we repent for them.
And so we offer our prayers to God as instruments that God can you choose to use,
to grant forgiveness and healing to that person.
that person. Right and if someone thinks
Well, you know, that shouldn't count.
Like, why should your repentance count?
You know, God chooses to use it for your salvation.
Right.
And it's all mercy.
It's all mercy.
And why wouldn't it count?
Because again, the problem is not how the departed person feels.
The problem is not that God is angry with the departed person.
Yeah.
God loves the departed person.
So if someone has sinned against me and dies, and I pray to God, and I say, I have forgiven
this person, please forgive this person, their sins, why shouldn't that count as repentance?
Yeah. Yeah. Or if someone I love has done something I know, and I go, and in their name,
try and fix it in the world, why would that not quote unquote, count?
Yeah, because it's a legalistic view, you know, or a sort of a financial view, you know.
If you have a correct view of repentance, right, I find out my departed loved one,
swindled somebody and I go and I give the money back to that person and make that person whole
and apologize on their behalf, right, and heal that. And I in the person my loved one swindled
and as God to forgive that person, right? Like, again, I don't understand why this is complicated.
Yeah. Yeah. So other than we have a weird messed up view of what repentance. Yeah. Which we do.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. And so I mean, so all this is relevant because
none of this applies to people who are in internal condemnation.
because all of this is talking about people who are in that intermediate state
Yeah, during this age. Yep. That's when we're doing the praying. Yep. Yep.
So it's not about quote unquote praying people out of hell.
If if if hell is your own is means eternal condemnation to you
Right, you know, so you could say well wait
Are are people who are experiencing eternal life going in the age to come going to pray for those experiencing eternal condemnation in the world to come?
I'm gonna be like
What?
So like there's literally nothing speaking to that anywhere in scripture or our tradition.
Yeah.
That's not what I'm talking about.
Right.
So we definitely, this is going to be a cheap shot.
Oh, but it's kind of an important cheap shot.
Important.
We don't and the Orthodox Church have Thomas Aquinas' thing about how people enjoying
eternal
life in the world to come are going to be more happy because they're going to watch the
people suffering in eternal condemnation.
If I didn't know that was true, I would not imagine that it was true that he actually
said that but well, so you got to give the qualifiers.
Okay.
It's from Tertius Partis.
It's based on his notes.
He didn't actually write it.
Okay.
And write at the end of it's at the end of his life.
Didn't he say?
Yeah, I got a lot of stuff wrong.
But well, this was after that, but it was from his note.
He didn't finish it.
Oh, I see.
Okay.
Right.
So they did it from his notes.
Had he lived, he might have edited that out or said something different or framed it
somehow or whatever.
But Nietzsche and everyone else has been quoting that for a couple hundred years now.
So it's been received as a thing.
That is no part of, I'm just saying that's no part of Orthodox tradition.
If Roman Catholics want to come to me and say that's no part of Roman Catholic tradition,
I'll be happy.
We rejoice. I don't say good. Yes. Good. This is when we're we're together on this. Yes. Yeah.
Yeah. So yeah. So okay. We've spent this whole half disambiguating what does happen to Hades.
You know, right. Long-term. So Hades, the underworld, that intermediate state. However we want to talk
about it, whether we want to talk about it as the underworld and those kind of quasi-spatial terms
or the intermediate state in sort of quasi-temporal terms.
This is part of the present age, the current creation, right?
This world over against the world to come, right?
And so it is something that is destroyed at the last judgment.
And actually, actually, though a lot of people I don't think have ever really thought
this through, both what we call heaven and what we call hell.
in our comments.
and sort of modern American parlients,
right, these intermediate state places,
right, cease to exist.
Because there's gonna be a new heavens, right?
It's not just a new earth but a new heavens.
Notice though, so there's a tripartite division
in the scriptures.
There's the heavens, the earth, and under the earth,
right, the underworld.
Notice there's a new
heavens and a new earth, there's no new underworld. How about that? No basement. Right. So there's
sort of a contrast here, right? Isaiah 24 verse 21, for example, talks about the purification
of the heavens.
Yep. Yep.
Uh, it says on that day,
the
Lord will punish the host of heaven in heaven and the kings of the earth on the earth.
There's a justification going on.
Right.
And this is dealing with the spiritual powers, right?
The spiritual powers.
Yeah.
Right.
But then there's a new purified heavens, right?
Purified of them and new earth.
But then in terms of Hades, you get Revelation 20 verse 14.
Yeah, which said...
then death and Hades were thrown into the lake of fire. This is the second death, the lake of fire.
So Hades is going to be gone.
So this is the ultimate disambiguation. Right? We're good talking about what comes next.
Tonight. We're talking about after
after the day of the Lord, after the last judgment.
after the resurrection of all the dead,
after the glorious appearing of Christ.
What comes after that for those who experience condemnation?
Right.
And even though we're using the eternal condemnation language,
and the biblical idiom, this is the condemnation of the age to come.
Yeah, right.
Literally the condemnation of the age,
and we age to come.
Not this age.
So these are two different things.
And as we said back at the beginning of this first half,
if you want more on Hades and the underworld
and this age and the harrowing thereof,
we've done a couple episodes about that.
So now the rest of tonight's episode
is gonna be about that eternal condemnation,
that condemnation of the age to come.
the people who opt out of
eternal life and the new heavens and the new earth.
All right, that said, we'll be right back with the second half of this episode of The Lord of Spirits.
webinar with Toss. Jesus' last words to disciples were go and make disciples of all the nations.
Unfortunately, many parishes are struggling to follow this commandment.
In my new book, Reclaiming the Great Commission, I offer a roadmap to help us get back on track.
Drawing from my 20 years of parish experience, holy scripture, and insights from research
and visits for churches across the United States, I discuss how you and your community can
implement changes that will transform reviral.
Can we new your parish?
You'll learn how to diagnose, remove the barriers you face, deal with resistance to change,
define what a healthy parish looks like, lead with purpose, and create a parish health plan.
Written for clergy, council members, ministry leaders, small groups, and all committed
parishioners, this book will help any church in its journey to reclaim the Great Commission.
Reclaiming the Great Commission is now available on paperback ebook and audiobook at store.
www.enginefei.com. That's store.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Steven Damick and Father
Steven DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
Hey, welcome back everybody.
It's the second part of the show.
This is a pre-recorded one, so don't come.
Or if you do call, I mean, who knows what'll happen, but yeah, let us know what happens. Yeah. I'm kind of curious
But yes, so we will not be taking your calls because
Again, I am across an ocean from where I normally am
The father's even still living in his swamp
Not one of those low grade oceans. It's right. It's one of the big ones
One of the big ones. Yeah
Yeah, the one that has Atlantis underneath it somewhere
Okay.
Okay, so or does it find out on another episode? Yeah, a completely different episode of Lord
of Spear. That would be that would be fun actually to do it as Lantis episode. Well, that
would just be a flood episode within Atlanta sections. Yeah, of course. Of course. Yeah. But
you know, yeah, because I read all that stuff. I'll like the stuff that's in Plato and so
forth. I read that for a paper that I was...
working on a number of months back and boy, it's fun.
And there's giants in the Greek version too. So that's great.
But that's not what we're talking about at this particular episode. We've just disambiguated
where people go when they die in this age with the life or death as it were of the age to come.
And we're talking about the death of the age to come in particular. The eternal condemnation,
The kind of nation
of that age, the age that has no end.
And so, yeah.
So there's, and it's particularly
we're talking about what the biblical language,
what language is the New Testament use?
Yeah, a lot of people like to think
that the Old Testament is the fire
and brimstone part of the Bible,
but it turns out there's language
for eternal condemnation in the New Testament.
And it's some pretty frightening imagery.
It's images that don't
all like work with each other as images.
Like you can't really super combine them.
I mean, there's some combinations you can make,
but it's really about different angles
from which to describe an experience
that is very difficult to describe.
And you're not supposed to like it,
or be comfortable with it.
And that's kind of the point.
Yeah, the purpose of the language, right,
to present this as a terrible...
terrifying possibility to motivate you avoided. Yeah. Right. That that's sort of the
whole point. And cards on the table. The main reason we're focusing on the New Testament
is that most of the people who disagree with the apostolic teaching on this point are
at least a little bit more C and I. Yeah. They're like, Oh, that's the old testament. And
That doesn't really apply now.
Ruby, old test.
of the ultimate God.
Which, you know, if you think that, welcome to Lord of Spirits podcast, because obviously
it's the first episode, right?
But so just for the sake of laying this out clearly, right, and laying out that it
is the apostolic teaching since, you know, the apostles produced the New Testament.
we're focusing on the new testament in this in this half.
Not to say we won't mention anything from the Old Testament, but we're focusing on the
New Testament that it's have to show.
Oh, no.
It's the good loving New Testament God who everybody claims to like who is saying these
things and setting out this terrifying possibility.
I was tongue in cheek there about there being a different New Testament God just to clarify.
Sometimes we have to.
going to clip that out in.
right, right? No. I am opposed to the
marcyanism that results from the
other view. Wait. After 200 hours of
the Lord of Spirits podcast, I
Yes, I hope that you've been
got moderately getting how salty I
feel in the third half. I may
express just how much to stay
I have for that particular view.
But for now, right? One of the one
of the sort of primary images for
eternal condemnation.
is the lake of fire.
And that sort of a hackneyed over-materialized version of that stands behind,
I think, sort of the popular contemporary perception of hell.
Yeah. Like what I like to call, you know, far-side as catology,
where depictions of hell are always like people standing in kind of like lava pits,
you know
with flames coming out of the ground
and usually there's some kind of...
Yeah, he routed a bunch of fire,
getting poked with pitchfork.
Yeah, demon with a pitchfork or a trident.
Yeah.
Usually tridance, I've noticed.
They talk about pitchfork, pitchfork,
but they always draw tridance.
So go figure.
Oh, is it a Neptune thing?
I don't know.
I mean, I own an actual pitchfork,
but I do not own a trident.
Now if it has...
than three, it's technically not a Trident. That's true. Sometimes you get these things that
look kind of like tridance, but have five. Quadristic. Yeah.
Pentant, yeah.
Yeah.
Venition, not a Trident. Pentant, Pentant. I don't know.
Literally means three teeth.
You start talking to the pitch for it.
Trident, three teeth. There's a metamology for you everybody. Good night.
Father Andrews work has done here.
That's right.
Exactly.
So yeah, but the
Lake of Fire is not meant to convey that imagery.
A lake of fire is,
imagine a lake, a big depression in the earth,
and it's full of fire.
So this isn't a cave with some fire in it.
It's not the fire caves of Bejor, it's not.
It's right.
And so the imagery is of being thrown into a fire,
not a place that has some fire in it.
The Lake of Fire M-
is it found in the Old Testament per se? Daniel 7, which we've come back to many times with the
enthronement of the Son of Man, when it talks about the judgment, describes a river of fire,
which is not the judgment, not the Kaahoga River in Cleveland, much to my surprise.
Yeah, although it has been a bleed.
Yes, on occasion. So this is a hypothesis because as we're going to talk about the Lake
of Fire imagery shows up in other Second Temple Jewish literature. Hypothesis that there
is a connection between this river fire and Daniel and the Lake of Fire, the idea being
the river pools into a...
lake. Yeah. It seems odd that river of fire, lake of fire would be completely disconnected,
right? Especially since the main place where we see the lake of fire imagery is the book of Enoch,
which is obviously influenced by Daniel 7 in a bunch of places. Yeah. Related to the
Son of Man and other things, right? So there is likely a relationship there, but we don't have
the data to like, conclusively.
show. So this is just sort of an
Occam's razor thing.
Right?
That those are probably related.
But we do get this imagery of the
lake of fire in First
Inek. It's the place where the
watchers get chucked for their
sin and wickedness, right?
It's tardorous. It's the best.
It's the deepest part of the of
the underworld, right? It's the
horrible place of punishment for
demonic powers.
And so when the Lake of Fire comes up in the New Testament, it's also kind of unsurprising
that it's in the two books of the New Testament that are most influenced by the Book of
Enic, those being the revelation of St. John and St. Matthew's Gospel.
The Book of Revelation, it comes up of course as you might expect at the end and just
like and
specifically in Revelation 19 verse 20, 20 verse 10 and
verses 14 and 15 of chapter 20.
And that context must much like first,
Enic, right, death,
80s, as we read in the last half, the beast,
the false prophet, the devil, right,
all of those demonic prayer, I'll get chucked into the into the lake of fire.
Also, however, along with them are those who received
the mark of the beast, meaning those who, those humans who joined with the demonic powers
who allied themselves with the demonic powers and their rebellion against the hatred of God.
Wait, are you saying it's not people who have credit cards or people who get some kind of medical
intervention? Just say medical intervention there. We're not, yeah. Say it once again, the mark of
the beast if you read Revelation.
of the beast is talked about in tandem with a mark of Yahweh, a mark of the Lord.
It's just that one.
Whenever you save them, the mark of the beast is, there has to be a corresponding one for
faithful Christians.
Yeah.
So if it's a barcode tattoo, then there's going to be some kind of divine QR code issued
by the church on people's foreheads.
Yeah.
out everybody. It's actually about what you do.
you. Yeah. Yeah. But so yeah. So unless your proposal, anybody who proposes X is the mark
of the beast to you, you have to say, okay, is there a holy X that stands in contrast
to it? Right. So is the church issuing a different vaccine? Is so otherwise it can't
be the market of beast.
Things can be bad without being the mark of the beast also.
Yes.
Not everyone you disagree with is Hitler.
Yeah.
And my favorite from recent years is there's now something called the forerunner to the
mark of the beast.
Which I'm like, is that a theological category now because I don't know.
Again, things can be bad without being the mark of the beast.
Yes.
You don't have to, it's not all the enough.
two things can be bad.
Right?
Like...
So, but as I mentioned,
the Lake of Fire language is also used in Matthew,
specifically in Matthew 25 verse 41,
and this is the last verses,
this is the end of the parable of the sheep and the goats.
Yeah.
Yeah, where you get...
Jesus says...
I mean, again.
This is Jesus speaking, by the way, everybody.
Then he will say to those on his left,
depart from me, you cursed
into the eternal fire to prepare it
for the devil and his angels.
Now this is important
because
notice he says that the fire is prepared
for the devil and his angels.
the devil and his messengers, meaning not for humans.
Yeah.
The purpose of the lake of fire was not for humans.
Say, humans that God hated and created to be vessels of His wrath.
Sorry, Calvinists.
Right.
But for the devil and his angels.
So, as in Revelation,
Right, the humans who end up there, it's...
It's because they've decided to sign on with the devil and his angels.
The devil and his messengers.
That's how they end up there.
What is this fire?
We're not talking about material fire as we mentioned with the far side thing.
This isn't like people are literally, I mean it is after the bodily resurrection.
But it's still not a literal place,
literal material place of literal material fire
where people are set on fire.
Wait, I'm not supposed to get my eschatology
from Jack Chick Tracks either.
No.
Because it's funny.
I now have thanks to a very kind listener
of the Aureaapigas podcast.
I have in my studio a complete set
of all the currently in print Jack Chick comics.
And whenever he depicts out,
I mean, that's what it always is.
big flaming space with you know
demons with pitchforks are really happy to see you and stabbing you in the butt.
You know, it's amazing. I mean, that would be, that would be a kind of hell for them,
I imagine, because it would have to get boring. But, but yeah, as we mentioned, in the contrast between
Dante and Milton.
The answer to the question, who's the boss?
Angela is the boss.
In hell, an eternal kind of nation.
Is not Angela or Samantha or Mona?
Definitely not Tony.
Definitely not him.
The answer is nobody.
Right, because it says in the scripture that all those who get tossed into all those who get tossed in the lake of fire are tormented forever and ever.
Right, and it was prepared.
Heard specifically for the devil and his angels to be tormented forever, forever,
there, right? That's what we're told. That's what it says by scripture.
So he's not in charge there. Right. And the reason I'm emphasizing this is not just
we have this wrong idea in our head due to Milton, but
people have this idea in their head. And again, we're going to we're going to we're
We're gonna, cards at the table, we're gonna be going after Universalism head-on.
in the third half. Okay. People will act as if if some person ends up experiencing eternal
condemnation that somehow the devil has won. Right. The devil has claimed this person.
No, no, the devil is a loser. Again, welcome to the Lord of Spears podcast. Right. This
is one of our frequent themes. The devil is a loser. Right. Right. Right. Dragging
Think someone down with you is not winning.
Yeah.
That's not winning. He doesn't have a kingdom of any kind. We are not Greek pagans.
Or actually almost any kind of pagan. But yeah, yeah. But so what's going on with this
fire imagery is not just, hey, being on fire is an image of horrible, horrible pain, which,
which of course it is, right, of suffering, right?
It's a bad thing that you want to avoid.
But this is the fire that comes from God, right?
See death by holiness.
See Nadab and Abahu, the fire that comes out of the presence of God, and consumes them.
Right? So this is about God's holiness.
When the wicked come into the presence of God's holiness, right?
It's compared to the scriptures to fire because
This is pain or suffering, right? Even when like think of Isaiah, Isaiah comes into the presence of
God's throne and is like tearing his clothes and it's like I'm undone, right? I have a man of
unclean lips for a people with ugly right, let alone the devil, right? So this is talking about
the experience of the presence of God by those who are confirmed in their wickedness,
right?
That's the imagery that's going on here.
But as we talked about, when we've talked about mortality
and human death, and the ways in which that's a mercy
or a grace from God, if you don't have that,
they'd have an abahood drop dead.
age to come, no one's going to die.
Right. In that sense, so this sense of physical
that. Right. Because the resurrection has happened and everyone was raised
incorruptible. Yeah. Everyone. And just a note here before we move off of the
fire imagery, because I wanted to just briefly touch on it in a couple of places,
the term Gihanna is used and we talked about this back in the
the Catholic Odyssey episode, the way the term Gehenna is used. And in some of the church
fathers, they used the term Gehenna as opposed to Hades in order to do what we were disambiguating
in the first half. They'll use Gehenna to refer to eternal condemnation and as opposed
to Hades to refer to in this age.
And we mentioned in that episode how it's a reference to the value of Hennum.
The reason I mention it here is that you get the garbage fire explanation, which it seems
like maybe isn't true.
Maybe it burned garbage there.
But rather, that's connected to the history there of Israel having offered their first born
to Molech there, the demonic worship that went on there.
It's also a-
next to the mountain of God. So you have the geography, right?
Symbolism there. But so I thought we should at least comment on that because the word
gets for more on how that word is used in the New Testament C previous episode. But because some of
the church fathers use Gehenna as their other word to talk about eternal condemnation, I thought it
that we're at least mentioning that here.
Yeah.
It's not clear in its New Testament usage which it's referring to.
Their place is where you could argue it's being used as a synonym of Hades.
Gotcha.
But yeah, so there's that.
So the next sort of major image that's used for a turtle conumination is outer darkness.
This is where the weeping and the gnashing of teeth are happening.
Hello, Mormon friends.
No.
So this is a term they use somewhat differently, but we won't go into that for our purposes
here.
This is the term that's used in Matthew 8 verse 12, Matthew 22 verse 13 and 25 verse
30. And it
All three of those cases, as Father Andrew mentioned, it's connected with the imagery of
weeping and gnashing of teeth.
Yeah, which, I mean, people know what weeping is.
But I think gnashing is not something people tend to think too much about these days.
I get some Bible word.
And that's, you know, gnashing of teeth.
Yeah, and that's usually people tend to read that, I think, at least the way I've mostly
Yes, he is.
and hurt it interpreted in general,
the American Christian circles is
that this is an imagery of suffering.
It's, it's, it's,
or an outer darkness is.
Yeah, it's grinding your teeth
is what gnashing your teeth is like.
Grrr, yeah.
Yeah.
You know, like your dog,
not what it,
like what your dog grows at you.
Yeah.
That's not at all what it is biblically.
Biblically and even in Greek literature
outside the Bible by the way.
that imagery is used to describe madness.
Yeah.
Madness the way we talked about it in our madness episode.
Yeah, like foaming at the mouth kind of thing.
Yeah.
Like think of the Gerasine Demoniak out in the tombs naked, right?
Or think of Nebuchadnezzar as we talked about in that episode, be reduced to sort of
this bestial state.
And so that's sort of the, and you can find this all kinds of places in Job at one point.
Job says that his enemies gnash his, gnash their teeth at him, right?
Meaning they're sitting there like enraged, right?
They're angry, right?
They're descending upon him, right?
Like wolves to destroy him violently, right?
that they grind their teeth at night because...
Man that...
Yeah, yeah, I mean, it shows up about that. It shows up a bunch of times in the in the Psalms and it's
every time it's about
you know the wicked gnashing at gnashing their teeth at the righteous, you know, yeah, yeah
And so this is a this is a good place to point out with this outer darkness that the different types of language used are not
on a wouldn't be literal level compatible.
Like fire and darkness are strictly speaking opposites.
Yeah, how can outer darkness have a lake of fire in it?
Right.
So if you take it at that very literal level, it's contradictory. But of course,
as we already mentioned, that's not how this is to be understood.
Right? And so we're getting different imagery for something that we fundamentally can't
can't understand.
from our embodied human perspective now
with our pre-resurrection bodies, right?
We can't understand what that's going to be like.
And so we're given imagery that pertains to
our bodily existence in this age as different metaphors.
Yeah.
Right?
So we can't understand what that would be like.
But if you've ever been camping,
You know, where there's sort of no ambient light on a dark cloudy night, right?
There's no ambient light for the city or anything around where literally you can put your
hand in the front of your face and you can't see anything, right?
Or if you've taken one of those cave tours where at some point they'll say, okay, everybody
turn your flashlights out.
I went on one of these when I lived on Guam because there's a lot of caves on Guam and
We'll turn our flashlights out in the tour guide.
goes this is what it's like in the heart of an unrepentant sinner. I'm not kidding. I was like whoa.
Wow. I know. But just feel bad and everything will brighten up.
Um, um, so, uh, yeah, but that is, that is a, that is a terrifying experience.
Yeah, for us.
It is age to be in that kind of darkness, right?
Right?
Especially if you hear weeping and gnashing of teeth going on around you.
Yeah.
Little freaky.
Right.
It's freaky.
So, this is an image of terror and madness.
This is bad.
This is something I want nothing to do, no part of, right?
Being set on fire very clearly, right?
This is something I want.
No, I do not want to be thrown into a fire, right?
So this is...
imagery of, right, terror, madness, right, suffering bad stuff, right, stay away from it, right,
do the other thing. Eternal life is what we want, right. And then the third sort of major
one is references to the second death or eternal death. And eternal death there is like
the death of
the age to come. The first death being physical death.
Visit, right. Right. And this gets used in Revelation 2 verse 11, 20 verses 6 and 14 and 21 verse 8.
And the last two of those, the lake of fire is said to be the second death.
Yeah. So there's a linkage between these images.
Right. Even though they're not like directly, you know, the same thing.
So what what kind of death is this?
getting talked about, right? Because there's another group of people who are we're only
going to pick on here. Since the third half will be reserved for a whole other group of people
who it's generally called annihilationism. Yeah, which is this teaching that good people
in the life of the age to come get to be with God in heaven. But bad people are just erased.
Yeah, see you.
exist. Yeah. So there's a bunch of problems with that. One of them is that there is no sense
of the word death in the Bible that refers to annihilation. Yeah, I mean, even physical death
doesn't mean ceasing to exist. Right. And we've talked about this before, but bears repeating,
say John DeMascus summarizes this.
The reason I come back to St. John of Damascus a lot is that if you read his found to wisdom
he summarizes, you know, he's in the eighth century. So he summarizes a
lot of things from the preceding fathers and from scripture and
synthesizes it. Yeah, he's great. He's just a schoolmaster. You know, he's really just yeah, he's like a
catechist really is in that text. So if you're looking for good definitional statements, right?
Bye.
Like I need to explain, as we're about to,
there's physical death and there's spiritual death
and how they relate to each other.
You go to say, John of Damascus, he's got it pulled together
and can give you sort of a definitional statement, right?
To help convey it.
Physical death, separation of the soul from the body,
spiritual death, separation of the soul from God.
So this obviously isn't eternal physical death.
Right, because there was a resurrection
and everyone was bodily resurrection
and it's universal.
incorruptible.
So everyone is bodily raised, so it's not eternal physical death.
That's off the table.
Meaning this is eternal spiritual death.
This is eternal separation of the soul from God.
And again, separation here is not spatial language.
Yeah, because God is everywhere present.
Yes.
It is not implying that there is some quote unquote place.
It's a material sense in the age to come where God isn't
It's sort of any more than there is a place now where God isn't yeah, it's sort of like being detached from God or unplugged
So to speak but people could experience spiritual death nonetheless right yeah, and that's what produces a physical death
We talked about that in the the episode on the soul for example
So that's the kind of eternal death we're talking about
Let-
Let me add this about annihilationism.
The biggest problem with it is that there are zero examples, zero examples in the universe
of things that cease to exist in the terms that they mean that.
Here we go.
matter, energy, all that.
Yeah.
I mean, it's just pure concept.
It really is.
It's just pure concept.
A pure modern concept.
Yeah.
Relating to, as we've talked about before, the modern dichotomy between being and nothingness
or between fact and fiction.
Yeah.
Which we think in mathematical terms.
There's a one and there's a zero.
Right.
and where to exist means to have bodily physical...
material corporality. Right. But in ancient terms and in biblical terms, as we've talked about
before, the opposite of being is chaos. Right. So yes, you have seen, there are plenty of examples
of places where there was a tower and now there is not a tower. Yeah, it went from being to chaos.
Right. But yeah, the tower did not cease to exist. The matter which made up the town.
is all still around. It's not the form of a tower anymore. It's a organized and set in order as a tower anymore.
When an animal dies, it doesn't cease to exist.
It dissolves into its component parts
and the energy that animated it dissipates.
But neither cease to exist, in the sense that annihilation is a-
talking about people ceasing to exist. So there are zero examples of anything God created
actually ceasing to exist. So before you can even argue that this is going to happen
to some humans, you have to construct an argument that it happens at all.
Yeah, that it's actually a category that it's a thing that can happen. Right? Good luck.
about it. John's dot's gone so he can't help you.
So we have to point out, so, and we've tried to be clear here when we use the term eternal.
Because of course that we've mentioned this many times on the show, right?
Sort of the pop conception of eternity is endless succession of moments in the way that
we currently experience time.
Right?
And.
and go watch the last season of the good place.
If you wanna know why that's a problematic,
come.
Oh, right.
Yeah.
And that's not what we're talking about.
We're talking about what it literally says is the life
or the death or the condemnation of the age,
which is referring to the age to come.
Right.
But everywhere where these things are referred to together,
these things being eternal life and eternal condemnation
eternal life.
life in eternal death or however it's raised wherever the two are talked about.
They're always spoken of as equally ultimate.
Yeah, and probably the the Locust classicus for this maybe which Orthodox Christians should
all be familiar with because this is read at our funerals is from John chapter five, right?
Where the Lord talking about the resurrection.
I'm just going to read this.
He says, truly, truly I say to you, an hour is coming in now.
It is now...
here when the dead will hear the voice of the Son of God and those who hear will live.
For as the Father has life in Himself, so He's granted the Son also to have life in Himself,
and He's given Him authority to execute judgment because He is the Son of Man. Do not marvel at
this for an hour is coming when all who are in the tombs will hear His voice and come out. Those
who have done good to the resurrection of life and those who have done evil to the resurrection of,
I think it's translated variously, judgment, damnation, condemnation.
But anyway, the point you're making, there's two outcomes.
They are both through resurrection.
One is life and the other is this condemnation.
Right.
And there's no proviso on the second one.
Yeah, it doesn't say, oh, well, one of these is temporary.
Yeah.
and of course Matthew 2546.
Again at the...
end of the parable, the sheep and the goats.
Yep.
These will go away into eternal punishment,
but the righteous into eternal life.
Again, perfectly parallel.
Yeah.
Again from the mouth of the Lord Himself.
This is Jesus.
The punishment of the age, the life of the age.
So if you want to say that one of those ages has an end,
then the other one must also.
Right?
Yeah.
Um,
When the same word is used in the same sense twice.
It becomes really hard to argue that it means two different things.
Without a lot of further evidence to point to.
And honestly, right, this is the place where we have to acknowledge again,
this isn't really complicated.
This is really simple.
This is taught all through the Scriptures.
It's so plain and so simple.
And yet our ability to confound it is bizarre.
And my favorite summary of it, this is where we are going to dip into the Old Testament
because this is my favorite summary of it.
Because it's so clear.
Yeah.
Because at the end of the book of Deuteronomy, the end of the Torah.
Deuteronomy 30 versus 15 through 20.
Yes.
So after God tells the whole story of creation
and gives all his commandments, everything, he says this,
see, I have said before you today,
life and good, death and evil.
If you obey the commandments of the Lord your God
that I command you today by loving the Lord your God,
by walking in his ways and by keeping his commandments
and his statutes and his rules,
then you shall live and multiply
and the Lord your God will bless you in the land
that you are entering to take position of it.
But if you're hard...
Our turn is away, and you will not hear, but are drawn away to worship other gods and
serve them.
I declare to you today that you shall truly perish.
You shall not live long in the land that you are going over the Jordan to enter and possess.
I call heaven and earth to witness against you today that I have set before you life and
death, blessing and curse.
Therefore choose life that you and your offspring may live, loving the Lord your God, obeying
his voice and holding fast to him, for he is your life and length of days that you may
dwell in the land that the Lord swore to your fathers.
to Abraham, to Isaac and to Jacob to give them.
What about people who object? Well, that was just for Israel at that particular moment in time.
Well, see every place where Christ says how the old or Timmel will pass away from the
yeah, for the law, etc, etc, etc. We'll read the book of Hebrews
Yeah, where it talks about how the penalties of the
covenant are much more severe. Not the opposite. Oh, no, no, but this is super clear.
Right. Christ says, if you love me, keep my commandments. That sounds an awful lot like
what God says here, right? If you love the Lord, your God by walking His ways and keeping
his commandments and his statutes.
Yeah.
You know,
a glowing lord.
your God obeying His voice, holding fast to Him, being faithful to it.
Like this is just so obvious and so clear.
And it's a matter of choice.
Yeah.
And and I should say, I mean, you can do just a quick search of the Bible and see
how many times loving God and keeping His commandments are paired.
And it's at least 25 in those exact words, at least in the ESV.
I'm sure we could come up with other ways of saying it.
and it's old in New Testament, it's everywhere.
If you love God, you keep His commandments.
Yes.
Yes, because again, love is not feelings.
Love is actions.
And, you know, the idea that love is feelings is what has brought about the divorce rate
in this country.
because guess what Phil?
go and go. All feelings of all kinds toward everyone. Yes. Right. And you either continue to act faithfully
when the feelings are gone, just like you did when they were there and they were that their strongest,
or you don't. And that's what ends up separating people. So when I say it's a matter of choice,
it's not a matter of choice like once. Right. Where you just, oh yeah, no. Yeah, I'll take the blessings
things in life. Thanks God.
Right.
So blessings in life, please.
Yes.
Cake or death.
Yeah.
Right.
Like everyone's going to take that one.
But how do you do?
How do you make that choice?
You don't make that choice intellectually.
You don't make that choice on one day.
Any more than you make the choice to be married to someone
intellectually on one day.
Right.
That choice is a pattern that emerges over your behavior over a lifetime.
about whether you're a faithful married person or not, right?
About whether you're faithful to Christ or you're not, but whether you actually love the
Lord your God or not, right?
It's a decision constituted by a thousand smaller decisions, right?
And so the person who refuses to repent, who refuses to worship God, who refuses to love
God and His neighbor, the person who refuses to do that.
is making the choice to reject the offer of life that God has extended to that
person. And God does not force his love on people. I mean this is awfully
blunt, but God is not a rapist.
Yep.
Yep, okay, he's not a kidnapper, he's not a human trafficker.
That's not, that's not.
his love on people. That's not love. Yes, I mean, that is because that wouldn't be love. Yes.
I mean, it seems to truly be love so one has to be able to reject it. Right. Right. Love sets the
other person free. And so eternal condemnation becomes a possibility because of the love of God
being actually love.
And because of his offer of life to everyone being sincere,
that means it's possible for a person to reject it.
And so eternal condemnation exists as this future possibility.
There's horrible possibility.
There's terrifying possibility.
The way it's described in the scriptures.
Yeah.
But a possibility nonetheless.
All right.
Well, that's the second half.
There's one more half to go because as you know everybody, it's a show and a half.
So we'll be right back after this brief break with the third half of the Lord of Spirits.
This is Andrew Williams. Since the advent of the internet, it has become increasingly
obvious that our society suffers from a pornography problem, and orthodox Christians are no exception.
While many practical resources are available to help those who struggle with pornography
news, these fail to address the problem at its deeper spiritual root, and to acknowledge
how it affects our whole society.
My new book, From Object to Icon.
The struggle for spiritual vision in a pornographic world shows how all of us can change the way we see,
how we can learn to see iconographically rather than pornographically,
whether or not we struggle with pornography use.
This book shows us how to stop objectifying others
and instead see the spiritual reality in everyone we encounter.
From object to icon is now available at store.inchantfaith.com
that storm.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father
Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
Welcome back. It's the third half of this episode of the Lord of Spirits.
podcast and once again, this is preview courted.
So despite what you just heard from the voice of Steve,
don't call now or do.
Again, it's up to you, but you probably will not get
to talk to us because that's not so.
We literally can't stop you.
We can't, I mean, right.
You can do what you want.
Like it's weird.
People can do things like not listen to a podcast
that they don't like and yet so many feel like they have to.
I don't know what that's up with.
What's up with that?
I love our heat listeners.
Well, because I hate listening to their comments.
So like, turned about spare play.
Right.
That's true.
But I mean, it's all that giggling that you do while you're listening to while you're
reading their comments.
Yeah.
So, okay, well, in the first half, we disambiguated the Hades slash hell to which the wicked are
consigned when they die in this age and then in the second
half, we talked about the various biblical images for eternal condemnation. And now in this
half, Father Stephen is finally going to get us canceled. By people who already don't like me,
so not really. There we go. Yeah. We're talking about the heresy of universalism. Yes, the condemned
Yes, conciliately condemned.
The rejection of apostolic speech
ignores universalism.
But I still start the triggering now.
Right.
Like if you really can't handle sustained critique
of universalism, if you are a person
who is a universalist for some kind of emotional reasons,
right?
Or reasons of sensitivity or something.
And you don't want to subject yourself to hearing
a sustained critique of it.
You should probably not listen
the rest of this.
podcast. Yeah. And I mean, that said, like I know, I know that some people are universalists
because they kind of can't bear the idea of, of eternal condemnation. And in some cases,
people are universalists because maybe someone they love killed themselves, cursing God,
or something like that and they're like well...
I don't want that person to be eternally condemned.
How can that possibly be?
I love them so much.
Which I mean, I get that.
Like I get that.
I get why people would feel that way.
But at the same time, I'll at least say
the hope of someone else's salvation
does not have to be founded on, frankly,
heretical teaching.
You're digging in the wrong place.
Yeah, or the
You need on that cap.
Yeah.
Now, if you're a universalist because you're like a pompous know-it-all, who feels smugly
superior to everyone else, go ahead and listen.
Yes, right.
Because a lot of this will be for you.
Yes.
So, and we don't feel for you.
This is directed at.
We're not feeling, because, you know, we, as you know, from the previous half, empathy
is dubious in general, or at least it's necessity.
but we do not have empathy for people
people who are pompous know it all and therefore pushing universalism.
Right. Well, yeah, I mean, I don't want to beat up on suffering and grieving people.
No, of course not because I have empathy being a high functioning sociopath, but
it's a bad look. Yeah. Yeah. But oh, yeah, I will, I will puncture windbags all day. That's,
That's, that's good sport. Amen.
But more a little more seriously, right?
Holding this up kind, we're going to go into more detail, but holding this up kind of
universalism doesn't do what you think it's going to do.
People do it to solve a problem, like some of the problems you've mentioned.
And
variety of others. So it's understandable, right, that you're looking to a solution to
that problem. And this presents itself as such a solution. But it has follow on consequences.
In your view of God, in your view of sin, in your view of repentance, right, that cause
those worst problems. And so there are better solutions.
But so let's let's go ahead and get it. Let me just get this out of the way too, right?
Like back at the beginning of the episode, I talked about here's the things we're going to get.
Just to save us some emails.
I mean, save me some emails.
And so, well, I didn't say I was going to read them, right?
Bandwidth, bandwidth.
The uh, I have read that all may be saying.
the David Bentley heart book. Yale sent me a free review copy when it was first released.
I read it. I didn't end up doing a review of it. I did do a review. They also sent me every copy of
David Bentley art's New Testament translation. I did a review of that because I thought while
there were portions I disagreed with, obviously, there were also things about it that were a value.
So I did a review because I could do a review like that. Here are the things I think are a value
you despite this.
places where I disagree. That all may be saved is one of the worst books I've ever read.
One of the worst theological books I've ever read. And I've read some bad ones. It is
a book and that's why I didn't write a review. I didn't have anything constructive to say
about it. Over the course of this half, people who have read it, we'll see.
why it's bad, but it's the kind of book that draws
cheers from people who already agree with its premise.
Because it's written from a perspective of,
this is the truth.
I'm going to primarily establish that truth
by ridiculing people who disagree with it
and knocking down straw man of an office.
position, which if you already agree with it, you'll rar-a if you don't, then it's
valueless.
Right?
Like it's not going to convince anybody.
But so yeah, so save your email saying, oh, have you read this book?
Good, it's arguing.
Is it Irrefeutable?
Save it.
Read it.
Not only is it Irrefeutable, it's laughable.
Okay.
But now, getting into the topic at hand, Quattta.
Okay. Right. So what we're talking about what we're talking about universalism
is not like the unitarian universalists. That's a whole separate. Right. Yes. We're not spending
use a half of an episode like Bashing on them, right?
Doesn't take that long, frankly. But we're talking about
people who believe some of whom are within the Orthodox Church to one degree or
another, and who believe in some form of apocodostasis, some form of universal
reconciliation to God. At minimum this means the idea that all humans will
inevitably be reconciled to God in the age to come.
Yeah, there's various ways people get to that.
But yes, that's where it ends.
Yes.
So that's defining the term universalism as we're using it, right?
That's the minimal.
And sometimes it goes beyond that, right?
So there are forms of apocotostosis where it's even the devil, the demons are all going
to be reconciled to God.
Right.
Going way further, but minimally it's the belief that all humans will receive eternal
life.
than the age to come, inevitably and eventually.
And then there's various forms it takes beneath that.
The most infamous, despite recent attempts at rehabilitation,
the most infamous proponent of this kind of view,
who took it to the extreme point was of course origin.
I have what is apparently news for some folks.
Origin, specifically on the point of Opal Custossus was condemned at the Fifth Hacking
Medical Council.
What?
And I say this not because I have taken a Tardis to 553 AD and walked into second
with a GoPro.
This is the second episode in a row that you've mentioned GoPro's, by the way.
GoPro's, yes.
Well, I feel like it's more specific than video camera and who knows sponsorship deal.
So right, and I don't have to.
In fact, if I did that, and I brought back the video.
And we watched the video with people fluent in Greek and
everyone agreed, you know what? They didn't even mention origin.
Not once in the whole video
It would still be a fact that the fifth annual
Geicumentical Council condemned origin on apocodostosis. Right because
because
That's not how holy tradition in the Orthodox Church works.
Yeah.
It is demonstrably easily to show that the church for century upon century upon century
has not only repeated what it says about the ecumenical councils. It is enshrined them in
in hemnography.
For, I don't know exactly how long,
but it's...
centuries at the very least, probably well over a thousand years. Right? Right. So, you know,
there are some people, and now for those of you who might be new to this discourse,
there are some people who say that the council did not condemn origin, or that it only said certain
kinds of things and not others, or whatever, you know, there's all kinds of variations on this.
and that later saint Justinian altered it.
Right, he pulled a fast one on everybody
and it's been a big mistake for all these 1600 years.
It's a big mistake, right?
That there are people who say that.
But that is not how Orthodox tradition works.
So if you're going to,
if you're like an Episcopalian,
by all means, make that.
Oh yeah, totally.
That's basically Anglican Episcopalian argumentation.
Right, you think the church was wrong about all kinds
of things for hundreds of years, right?
Yeah, right.
Sure, but, but, you know, to, to, to posit this idea,
You have to say that the Holy Spirit was not getting through to the church on something
this big for that long and across the entire geographic range of the church for centuries
upon centuries upon centuries.
Nor even the subsequent ecumenical councils that also confirmed that council and so on
and so forth.
It is a level of wrong that is
staggering to imagine for an Orthodox Christian.
Right. And if you think that that's a thing, and there are Orthodox people who think that
that's a thing, then on what basis can you say that any of the councils, or even the scripture itself,
are truly reliable because like, like, like, Nicaea, right? We all have things we say about Nicaea,
But we don't have the majority of the texts of the
like the minutes or whatever, everything was said at Nicaea.
We have less than we do about the fifth
ecumenical. Right. Right. So so so it is a massive
methodological problem. You are dismantling all of Orthodox
tradition to say that one of the ecumenical councils
didn't say what the church has for centuries upon centuries
said that it said. Right. That's that's what's actually at
stake, everybody. And now notice notice you said over
something this big. And this is something we have to call out too. Because, of course,
when folks who hold to some form of apocatostasis are arguing that their views should be tolerated
within the church, it's always, oh, this is a scatology. It's a side thing. It's not a major
thing. It's not a big deal. And then when they're arguing for their point, they say,
who disagrees with them, their God is a monster.
Right? And it's like...
Well, you know what?
Who God is seems kind of significant to me, theologically.
I'm just throwing that out there.
Yeah.
So if both sides admit that this is very key
to the whole view of God that it seems
that this is a major issue in fact,
yeah.
The kind of thing that an ecumenical council
weighs in on and did.
And therefore, it's obligatory.
But what's really going on here is that these folks
are making a Protestant argument
and say what you want.
to our Protestant friends about Protestantism,
Protestant arguments are not Orthodox arguments.
Right, and Orthodox arguments are not Protestant arguments.
Yeah, and in this case, it's a,
not all Protestants make this argument about the scripture,
but it is a Protestant argument.
The idea that there is an original text of the Bible
that is sort of the infallible one.
And I've seen this like in...
That's an error or infallible text.
Like I've seen this in statements of faith
on your websites.
The Bible is infallible in an inherent in its original manuscripts, which you got one.
In the autographs, right?
In the autographs.
That's the yes.
And then you use textual criticism and like the national statement of pens, you know,
this could be reconstructed with modern computer tools, you know, the rest of history didn't
have an inherent Bible, but now we've got it back.
Now we do.
Um
But the idea there is the authority there is not in the text as it currently
exists or has historically existed in the church. It's not in how it's been
received by the church. It's not in how it's been historically interpreted by
the church, but it's in the original text as it existed historically at the time
of its writing. This is why I say...
the proponents of apocotostasis are making the same argument. They're saying that the
church council, the ecumenical council, does not have authority as it has been received by the church.
Does not have authority in the way in which its findings have been promulgated,
but that the authority lies in what was actually said and done on the day historically as they want
to reconstruct it.
That reconstruction has no authority in the Orthodox Church, in the Orthodox View of
tradition.
Anymore than a modern critical scholar's reconstruction of what really happened to
be hide the Old Testament as any authority in the Church.
What has authority, the Scriptures have authority in the Orthodox Church.
This is how Orthodox tradition works.
They have authority in the Orthodox Church as they've been received and in
interpreted by the church historically.
Yeah.
Church councils have authority as they have been received and interpreted by the church
historically.
And the fifth ecumenical council has been received as an ecumenical council and historically
interpreted as having condemned origins specifically about the issue of Afoketastasis.
And there's no arguing that.
It is a simple matter of fact.
Yeah.
Right.
Alright, let's...
that you have to just deny reality to argue against that. That's how the Orthodox Church works.
Now, if to our non-Orthodox listeners, you may say, well, I disagree with that.
I say, okay, right? So for you, maybe as a non-Orthodox Christian, the condemnation of
of origin and universalism is an authoritative, right?
But as orthodox Christians,
for us it is. But it's also worth noting, right? And this is one of the problems, even accepting
the problem with their argument in the first place, like the structure of their argument that we've
just pointed out, right? Even their reconstruction doesn't make sense. Right? Because the narrative they
present is that sort of no one had any problem.
with origin except Saint Justain and.
Yeah, like it just came out of nowhere.
He was a secret nemesis or whatever.
Yeah, came in after the fact, I mean, there are maybe a few people who didn't like him,
you know, who are usually the people who the given reconstructor doesn't like in church
history.
But, but this is all kind of a bamboozled, it's like just Indian polls, right?
And again, this is not...
Controvertible, right? Is that origin was condemned, particularly on this issue,
over and over again at local councils by church fathers for a couple centuries leading up to
the Fifth Medical Council. The Fifth Medical Council was just ratifying what everybody else had
already done and making it the binding, binding of an ecumenical council.
Yeah, so even if the count-
so it never happened.
An origin never mentioned.
It still was the tradition of the church up to that point.
Yes, everywhere.
And this included, this included, most tellingly,
people who were admirers of origin in other regards,
or people whose biblical exegesis
and whose theology was dependent on origin,
Who will say?
right? They're these good things at origin, but and they specifically single out the most commonly
things singled out. Sometimes there's some other things too, but the most common thing singled out
about origin that they say is wrong is apoconostosis. Right. So they these great admirers of his say,
Well, in that one place at least he was way off.
So, beyond origin, right, there are a couple other figures.
These are actually saints, unlike origin, who are pointed to and said to be proponents
of apocatostasis. The two primary ones are
St. Gregory of Nissa and St. Isaac the Syrian.
And so people who reject the Church's teaching on this will point to them and say, Oh, we'll
see, look, there's these two saints who we're going to say held to some kind of apocotostosis.
Therefore we can hold to our albeit different form of apocotostosis.
And it's okay.
Right?
I mean, you see the flaw in that argument there.
end anyway. Right. Right. Like you're not even holding to the view you claim that St.
Held exactly. Just one that's in the ballpark. Right. And acting like he opens up the ballpark
for you to theorize for yourself. But there's an added problem, which is it's not entirely
conclusive that either of those figures were universalists. Yeah. And there's even like with
of St. Gregory.
of Nisa, for instance, there's actually, I mean, you could do some really quick Googling,
just right in like, was St. Gregory of Nisa a universalist? And there's actually a gazillion
articles out there showing in great detail about how he was not and how he taught eternal condemnation
and, and so forth. Right. Right. And so, and there's a relative
of POSITY of writings from St. Isaac the Syrian.
Yeah.
Right.
We have more from St. Gregory.
But and you know, you get people who quote mine and proof text church fathers will pull things out that kind of sound.
Right.
St Gregory of Nissa has this done to him all the time.
All the time people online pull out this quote from his life of Moses to say, oh, St Gregory didn't believe that the death of the first born actually happened at the Passover.
Well, it all you have.
to do is read the passages immediately before and immediately after the quote to see that he did.
Yeah. Right. So in the ways not to read church fathers, right? Looking for quotes,
especially having chat GPT look for quotes because it will make up a tristic quote.
It will. You can literally ask it and it will come up with citations that look great,
But I completely fall.
They're fake.
Yeah.
Yeah, yeah, but even using Google right?
Yes, you could quote mine the church fathers just like you could prove text the Bible if you pull verses out of context
To try and argue for anything
Yeah
But that's disingenuous and doing violent for them
But also there's sort of there are things that people like to freely interpret like someone saying that we should pray a saint saying we should pray for all of creation
There are saints who say we should pray for the demons and the devil and pray for
insects and pray for it, right? That doesn't make you a universalist. That doesn't make me,
mean you believe in apocosis, that doesn't mean you believe that they're all going to be
inevitably reconciled to God. In fact, the fact that you're praying for them kind of argues for
the opposite, that it's not inevitable, right? You can argue from praying for it that it's possible,
but that's not it.
even necessarily true. Right. One could pray for a demon. If a saint is being tormented
by a demon and he prays for the demon, he might do that as a way of expressing love for
his enemy without believing it's possible for that demon to repent, for example. Yeah.
Right. So it might not even be that they believe it's possible, but the act of praying for
Right means it tends to indicate it's not inevitable.
Right.
And you also have any time a saint reflects hope that all humans would be saved, would
find salvation, hope that all humans would be reconciled to God.
And that's like, oh, see, look, they believed in apoconnesens.
That's hope, right?
All Christians should hope that all people would be reconciled to God and find eternal life,
Because
The Old Testament says, God wills that all men be saved and come to the knowledge of the truth.
Right? So yes, we should want the same thing. Right? But wanting that and desiring that,
as we talked about with God at the end of the second half, is not the same thing as believing it's inevitable.
Those are the same thing.
Right. So beyond those historical issues, right. And that's really it for the historical
case. The whole historical case is trying and vain to undo the condemnation of origin
and trying desperately to identify a couple of church fathers who might have held a minority
opinion on this.
Right? That's the historical case for somebody believing in some kind of apoconostasis.
Everyone agrees that all of the rest of the fathers, the reception history of the Fifth
Aqueu medical council all condemn apoconostasis. I'll condemn this idea all point to the possibility
of eternal condemnation.
ambiguous. There is no ambiguity here in reality other than people trying to create it.
In the book I mentioned at the beginning of this half, right, the author in trying to argue for
for apocodostosis has to condemn ridicule the church fathers.
He calls them moral pigmeas.
For believing in eternal condemnation, that is the position you have to take to argue
for apocodostasis.
That's not him going too far.
That's the position you have to take.
You have to reject the church fathers and the saints as not knowing what they're talking
about, morally, theologically and religiously, in order to hold this view.
You have to cut yourself off from holy tradition to hold this view.
That's a bad consequence.
People see it as solving a problem but it causes bigger ones.
That's a much bigger one than the other problem.
So getting past that historical case though.
Universalism, apocotostasis.
Right again is the belief that God must
must, ultimately grant every human eternal life.
He must do it because otherwise he's evil.
They will often straight out argue this
or that if he doesn't grant every human eternal life
he is unjust, they will argue
But they will say, well, if he doesn't do it, he might...
He must be incapable of it.
Right?
And that lasted capable one, as well as the unjust one.
May remind people of some other discussions
we've had on this show, right?
Because deep down, deep down,
and this is the central argument of the book
we mentioned at the beginning of this half.
This is really a cal-
in this argument that they're making.
Yep.
So yes, I am saying right now, David Bentley Hart,
his argument in that book, deeply Calvinist.
It's Calvin by way of Carl Bart,
but it's still Calvinism.
All right, Carl Bart famously said,
everyone is reprobated, Adam, everyone is electing Christ.
So this is where this is going.
It's Calvinism where...
Everyone is elect. It's universal election.
Right. And this is based on displaying the justice of God. And as we've said before when we're talking about penal substitutionary
Atomment when we were talking about other related issues,
if God has some standard of good and evil that stands above him or some standard of justice that stands above him,
why aren't we worshiping that?
Hmm. Yeah, is God subject to necessity?
Right? This is arguing that God is subject to necessity that God must do something.
Namely, he must give eternal life to all of his human creations. And stop, pause for a minute
at how patently absurd that is. Because God created a human, he must share his divine life with
Thank you.
human eternally. He is obligated somehow. So now there is no grace, there is no gift in regard to
salvation. It is necessity. There is some old magic. There is some kind of, to which God is
beholden, right? This is absurd.
Right? This is absurd. And you can make
Sepistic arguments for it. Right? You make
Sepistic arguments for it. But it's absurd on the
face if you really think about it from the
perspective of biblical theology.
I know I'm not going to digress too far into this,
but it has to be said. Okay? It does have to be
said. Get ready for a spicy take.
You think it's been spiced you so far?
So there is a dirty secret in liberal theology.
It's a dirty secret now. It used to be open.
Right, but since the end of World War II, it's been a dirty secret.
Okay.
Okay. All liberal theology is at least vaguely mercy and I-
if not outright. Yeah, I mean they don't tend to like the Old Testament. Right. Old Testament
God, New Testament God. David Bentley Hart is exhibit A of this. Again, Book of Man should
have to begin this. Read what it says about the God of the Old Testament, calling him a monster,
calling him the devil. Okay. When it was pointed out to him, it was pointed out to Hart
that this made him a mark.
see a night. His defense was he doesn't believe the Old Testament God exists. So he's not a Marcy and
I. Wow. Okay. What? Yes. Okay. Well, where's he getting this? Where is this wild thing? Well, he's
beholden to a theological tradition that runs through 18th and 19th century Germany up in the 20th
century with guys like Yergen Moltmann, right? He's dependent on that.
It is deeply anti-Semitic. I know shocking 19th century Germans are deeply anti-Semitic, but
right? It is based on the idea that the God of the Jews, the God of the Hebrew Bible, the God
of the Old Testament. Right? Is a false God?
pagan God, a deficient God, right, and not the real God, right? And what that requires,
right? If you throw out the Old Testament and then want to reinterpret the New Testament,
right? You can't carry over any of those hebraic notions of who God is into the New Testament.
So who is God?
in liberal theology if we're not going to use the God of the Old Testament, who is the God in the New Testament?
It's Plato's God. It's the God of Greek philosophy. Because the Greek tradition is a European tradition and not Jewish.
And if you read the book we're talking about, David Bentley Hart's argument in that book
is deeply anti-Semitic and is seeking to replace the God of the Old Testament in Christian
theology with Plato's God, the same way that German theological tradition has been doing
for a couple hundred years.
anti-submit
Autism is just slightly less over.
You don't have to scratch that deep when you see what he says about the Old Testament
God, right?
But that's what's happening.
That's what's being put forward.
And all of this is liberal theological trajectory, right?
This is why if you read Nietzsche.
Nietzsche was always praising the God of the Old Testament.
Hmm.
Because Nietzsche despised liberal German theology.
That's the very form of Christianity he despised, right?
The most.
He actually says nice things about Russian Orthodoxy,
which he encountered through reading Dostoevsky.
And church.
But this is why he praises the Old Testament God.
test of my god he's trained to
to invert what these German liberal Christian theologians were doing.
And Hartzburg on Universalism is just a modern American incarnation of this.
This is another reason why this whole thing causes more problems than it solves.
We've now entered into this wildly problematic theological view from the perspective of the
Church and Church history.
from the perspective of common decency,
from the perspective of intellectual history,
right, this is deeply problematic.
Okay, this is not where you need to go
because someone you love died outside of the Christian faith.
You don't need to go to all this over that.
Okay.
I don't think that's why hearts there.
I think hearts there because actual Christianity
offense his moral sensibilities the same way.
it did those 19th century Germans. It's too gauche for him, right? It's too vulgar, too common,
right? But there are a lot of decent and good people who go down that road for those reasons.
And it's not a road you want to go down. There's nothing good down that road that's going to really help
you. Right? So that said, right? One of the problems.
I've personally experienced, I think this is probably true for Father Andrew too, you can
say.
In trying to talk about these issues with people, is that every individual person who believes
in some kind of universalism or apocotostosis always has their own nuances.
Yeah.
Right.
So I say
something critical of heart in his book, for example, they say, well, I don't agree with
him about everything. You know, I, you know, this and that is different. And this and the
other, right? But here's the thing, right? And it's even suggested sometimes that like,
unless someone takes the time to study every conceivable variation and answer each one individually,
Right? Like, oh, you can't then...
Comment.
on this issue. Of course, that's impossible. That's a way of saying, well, no one can
ever really discuss and argue with me. Yeah.
I mean, relatedly, unless the fifth technical counsel condemned the specifics of the particular
view that I hold of this, then I'm not, you know, my view is not condemned. Right.
Right.
And that's that's obviously not true. Right. Like the council of Nicaea and the council
No concept, no, Paul did not.
have to conceive of every possible minute variant of
Aryanism and semi-Aryanism to condemn Aryanism and semi-Aryanism.
Right? They condemned any view which says
that the Sun is different in substance from the Father.
Boom, done. Right?
And
So the council condemning the view that all will inevitably be reconciled to God by
some necessity means any view that has that feature regardless of all the other particulars.
If it has that feature, it's condemned.
And part of this two plays into this idea that people have received.
And I think it's due to this idea of the Gumina, which most people who talk about it don't understand.
The Gumina is basically like the idea of Pius' opinion, right?
Something that's not like a teaching of the church from which you can't disagree with
and things that are secondary or tertiary or right or really another way.
ways. So they've come to this idea that they're sort of on various issues of theology or various
topics of doctrine or various things about the way of life with an orthodoxy. There's
like a range of acceptable orthodox views. And as long as your view is somewhere in that range,
then you're okay, like you're allowed to believe it. People will phrase it that way. Am I allowed
to believe X. Yeah. Which...
is just not the right question.
Am I allowed to believe that the sky is purple?
Well, I mean, I can't stop you, but it's not.
Am I allowed to believe that 2 plus 2 equals 5?
Well, I mean, if you really want to,
Right? This assumes this basically has nested in it.
post-structuralist or post-modern presuppositions, that the truth is unknown and
or unknowable. Right? That there is no substantive teaching in the church on this
topic. Right? Therefore it's just the subject of conjecture and so various
opinions are allowed. But, uh, but then there may be.
there may be some that are disallowed too, but you know, and so there are things I want
to believe are true. And I just need to find out if it's okay. Yeah. Can I find true?
Can I find someone somewhere who said something like this? Ah, like permission. Yeah. Right.
And let me suggest a more radical solution. If it's a theological topic on which there
is there really is no teaching.
There is no authoritative teaching.
within the tradition of the church on it. You shouldn't have an opinion.
Yeah. Right? Like, just don't have one. Yeah. Because, because, because everything that is given
to us, I'll probably say more about this at the end, I think. But I just want to say here,
everything that is given to us in the church is for the sake of our salvation, not for the sake of
of having an opinion about everything.
Yes. Yes. This is why, and I know it can found some people. This is why there are things
I'm not interested in talking about. I'm not interested in talking about the date of
the Exodus. I literally don't have an opinion. I know about the late date. I know about
the early date. I know about the even earlier date. I don't know for sure that any of those
This 3 is the accurate date.
I believe the exit has happened, but I have no opinion on the date.
There's no church teaching about which date is correct.
So this is not a concern to me.
And you know, hey, if you want to have a really strong opinion about that, and I know people
who do, and you want to spend a lot of your life arguing about it, go for it, man.
I play wrestling video games, so I waste time too.
But, like...
It's the same level of usefulness in terms of salvation.
Right?
Being online matches of mortal combat and you having online arguments about the date of the Exodus
are of equivalent value.
Right?
And if you accept that, fine, that's your hobby.
Great.
So, but this issue is an important issue.
And this issue there is very clear church teaching on.
so it behooves
to accept it, especially if we don't like it.
Right?
Everybody believes in authority until authority tells you to believe or do something you don't
want to.
Yeah.
Right.
Everybody believes in the tradition of the Orthodox Church until it says something they don't
like.
Yeah.
I mean, obedience requires, almost requires that there be a difference of opinion.
You know, and that one person's opinion is going to
be the determining opinion.
Yeah.
Although in this case, it's not about personal opinions, it's about the teaching of the church.
Right.
Which is objective and accessible, not unknown and or unknowable.
Yeah, you should not have to dig.
Yeah.
You should not have to dig, right, to find...
Well, there's this thing right in my face, but I don't like it, so I'm going to dig.
I will try and find.
some way under it, around it.
Right.
Yeah.
I know.
I even saw someone, you know, like there's this
this made up word infernalism, which is used by
universalists to describe the teaching of the church,
frankly.
Yes.
People who hold the apostolic teaching.
Yeah.
And like it's used to describe someone like St. John
Chrysostom even.
And I'm like, you know, if St. John Chrysostom says something
and your response is, could I talk to somebody else?
Yeah.
I, it's hard for me to believe that your orthodox, like you can't get more mainstream than
him.
Second, second opinion, please.
Yeah.
Right.
And that's, that's not to say.
So for example, before, had a often email, right?
Like, thank you.
Somebody out there is going, we'll sing John Krizazum.
uh
the Nephilim were Cain's descendants and Abel's descendants. And you guys say this other thing, right?
That's what's coming, right? Go back and listen to that episode, right, where we lay out
facts about what the church fathers say, including that one. And our goal there is to reconcile
what the fathers say, where they apparently disagree. Yeah, not to say, well, I just disagree with
with this church father I want to be with
other one. And if you do that on this issue, right? So for example, you go to St. Gregory of
Nissen, you read something, you say, well, that almost sounds like apocotostosis. Then using this
approach, you would say, but all of the church fathers teach against that. So that can't be what
St. Gregory means, which I, if I recall correctly, is basically what St. Fortius says at one point.
Like someone's like, yeah, I might be misremembering, but he said, I think he said,
Well, some say that he taught up a
catastrophes, but that is a scandalous slur against him.
He would never have said such a thing.
Yeah.
So if you use that approach on this issue, right, you don't end up saying, well, I could
kind of read these two people to agree with me.
Therefore, I reject everyone else.
That's never our approach on anything on this show.
Sorry.
Yeah.
And so it's not worth it.
It's just, it's just not.
Yeah.
So that's kind of the,
if there is a positive argument,
right, made for apocotostosis,
it is that kind of positive argument
from some kind of divine necessity.
And we've just gone through how problematic that is.
Most of what you get though is not that, even, right?
The more sophisticated form like Hart's book,
you get that at least, right?
it probably
as it is, you at least get that as a positive argument, but most of what you get, including
in that book, are a bunch of negative arguments directed at particulars of a Western view
of how, which is also kind of problematic.
If most of your arguments for your position are just a bunch of
negative arguments against a particular other position.
You don't have any strong arguments for your position.
Right?
It's not even negative arguments against all of the other possible positions.
It's just one of them.
And making these arguments even weaker is the fact that they are arguments against that
particular Western view, which is kind of a caricature.
that accept the priest's positions of that very view.
Don't question those priest's positions.
So they're not even like strong,
undermining arguments to that view.
What do I mean by that?
Well, so for example, when they attack this Western view
of hell, they presume a certain definition
of what sin is.
Yeah.
the person believes that apocons.
Kodostosis accepts the pre-supposition that sin is the violation of a statute.
Yeah, it's breaking a rule.
Right. And that breaking that rule requires punishment. Right. And it even accepts the
pre-supposition that God must punish every sin. Right. Here we have divine necessity again,
must. Right. So where's the quibble? It sounds like you've accepted almost the whole
form. The quibble is then, oh, but punishment must be
proportional to the offense. So it says to that particular Western view, we agree with you
that sin is breaking a rule and it makes God angry and God has to punish sinners. And we
agree with you that God must punish every sin to its full extent. We just disagree about
the extent. Right? So already, if you've been listening to this show for very long, you
No.
that the Orthodox Church does not actually accept any of those pre-suppositions.
Does it accept that God must punish every sin to its full extent?
Does not accept that sin is primarily rule-breaking?
Does not accept that it makes God our right.
We already went over that.
This episode, right?
But they then argue that, so eternal punishment, punishment that goes on forever, is disproportionate
to sins that are committed in time in this life.
And so there's this really interesting passage
in Theodore Abukura.
So yes, Theodore Abukura.
Look him up on Wikipedia, everybody.
He's a medieval Arabic Orthodox Christian bishop
of Iran and has a massive corpus of writings.
Does not see.
A lot of which is not translated.
Yeah.
it's just still an Arabic. Does not seem to have, does not seem to be on any synch
audience that is to say like a calendar of saints right now, but he is spoken of as
a saint and a lot of medieval Arabic Orthodox Christian writings.
Later Christian writings refer to him as Saint Theodore Abu Kuru, but we couldn't find him on a calendar
that's why we didn't call him Saint. Yeah. Yeah. Because we're trying to be consistent about that too.
So, he...
has a number of sort of dialogues. They're a little bit Plato's dialogue-ish with frankly various
heretics. And one of those is with an originist, because Go figure in the 8th century,
the Adora Bacruz, Bishop of Puranon, Espatemia, thought origin was a condemned heretic. Go figure.
And the discussion with the originist is specifically about apocodostosis.
So he not only thinks that the origin of the kinetic, he thinks he's condemned on this
point.
And this is that sarcasm they're going to point out that I mentioned earlier.
And he based it so when the oratidist makes this very argument.
Right? Says, well, what you're talking about is an eternal punishment for sins that were committed in
time. And that's unjust, right? This whole justice thing where God has lived up to justice.
Because guess what? Like we said, they're basing this on Plato's view of God.
So we're originists, right? So then how does that work out? And
and the author's response
is essentially, I'm summarizing a little bit, how are you defining justice? Right? He says,
are you defining justice by nature? Like he says, if you're going by nature, I can think of
a lot of examples like where someone gets wounded and it takes a second, right? But the consequences
of that wound. The pain from...
that wound, the suffering from that wound is it heals. Take a long, long time. And he
says, are you talking about like justice like the legal system? He says, because I can
think of examples of the legal system, someone murders someone, it might take them a few
seconds to murder the person. But we then go and we execute them. And that executing
that was kind of permanent.
Right? That's right. And he says, you know, if if someone came and had sexual relations with your wife,
would they only be punished for the period of time it took for the sin to happen, for the crime to
happen right he's like what no right so
So, Theodore's counter-argument is simply, right?
You're using this word justice.
I don't think it means what you think it means, right?
Right.
Right?
That you're declaring something just but on no basis.
Yeah.
It's notable by the way.
Other than your own predilection.
I'd say it's notable, by the way, that Theodore Abelcura was also among at Mars Sabah
monastery where
St. John of Damascus was and in many ways is kind of like his intellectual successor, but he's really the
The first church father writing an Arabic
Which is pretty interesting all on its own
You know living in early Islam and so forth, but
Yeah, a lot of his writings are interacting with Islam. Yeah, I like I like the way that he reasons though
He just described like because
It's about like well, let's get this down to brass tax and stop you know up here in the
the rarefied ephemeral world of concepts that are interact with each other and down to,
okay, what is actually justice on the ground? How does this look? It's not just a theory.
This is real, you guys.
Yeah.
And there's also another pre-steposition that is just sort of accepted that we've already
kind of dealt with tonight is they accept the pre-sale-
that repentance is basically regret or guilt.
Yeah, surely everyone would feel bad when faced with eternal
damnation.
Yes.
If you're under a turtle cod omination, you would feel bad, right?
You might, you feel regret.
Like man, I wish I wasn't here, right?
But, you know, first of all, this assumes that, you know,
These departed.
condemned humans in the state that they're in
and demons have feelings the way we do.
But more important as we said earlier,
feelings are not repentance.
Yeah, I mean, there's a difference between
Judas and Peter.
Judas, it says explicitly in the scripture, felt regret.
But Peter actually was reconciled with the Lord.
Right.
They both had the same feelings.
Judas and Saint Peter had the same feelings
after they betrayed Christ.
They both betray Christ, they both had the same feelings, they did different things.
Based on those feelings.
So that just assumes feelings.
And therefore, they just assume that at some point in this state, they will quote unquote
repent.
They will quote unquote have their feelings change.
And really related to that, the idea, well, I mean,
And on a long enough timeline, right, I mean, wouldn't eventually everybody sort of wise
up, right?
You often within these views of apocodostasis to try to make them work, right?
Because generally these folks find like just full on apocodostasis.
Everybody dies.
Everybody goes to heaven.
Everybody's resurrected.
Everybody enjoys eternal life in the world to come, right?
find that somewhat distinct.
or at least some of the consequences.
Yeah.
Right? You point out to them,
so you're saying Anne Frank and Adolf Hitler,
right? Experience the exact same afterlife of eternal bliss.
I mean, that's what it comes down to.
Right. But
saying that it's that from the jump, right?
They recognize the problem.
And so what gets inserted is a purgatoryal idea of hell.
Yeah.
Yeah. And I say purgatoryal deliberately because basically they're taking the Roman Catholic conception of purgatory and
Trying to sort of refab that into a
Stopgap, right? So you say well Hitler's gonna have a real bad time for a long time before he gets to that internal bliss, right?
But this requires a whole bunch again of of presuppositions
that are foreign to
at least the Orthodox Christian tradition and the scriptures, right? Which, for example,
they're going to be published for some, punished for some period of time. Well, number one, time.
This assumes time works in the ancient times. Right? There's like, there's this really caricatured
view of the way purgatory works in Roman Catholicism, which to be fair, a lot of people in the medieval
Sure.
talk like that's their view. Oh totally. Yeah, I mean, it's not but
but Robert Catholics are more sophisticated about it. Yeah. And
the great Roman Catholic theologians of the Middle Ages were also
more sophisticated about it. But you get a lot of common stuff of just like,
hey, this intelligence is two years off purgatory, right? It makes it sound like
purgatories of place that experiences a linear succession of
moments the same as we do, right?
As I said, that's a caricature of what the Roman Catholic Church, the Thorotatively, teaches,
right?
But, but that's sort of what this is based on within these folks who believe it, Op.
O'Connor Stossus is that there's some time and they need that time like in order to
parcel off an amount of suffering because remember, their whole argument for this is based
on proportionality.
So there are some sins that are like really bad and something that are less bad and there's
a certain amount of suffering and you kind of need to use time.
I suppose you could use intensity.
There's a certain amount of suffering that then is the proper punishment for that individual
sin based on something.
Yeah.
I mean, you can see this is a kind of parody of purgatory.
You
There's just simply nothing of the scriptures for which you could derive any idea of this.
No.
Yeah.
The idea of making satisfaction, especially in terms of like, what you need to do this much
because for this.
Right.
So, like the Torah does not parse aloud like inflicting X amount of pain for X amount
of time in response to breaking this commandment.
Yeah, Noris there, I mean...
correct me if I'm wrong, nor is there even like a sense of like, okay, well, if you
killed someone, this is a sacrifice you have to make, but if you killed two people, then
you have to do twice as much, two bulls or whatever. Right. No. No. It's based around restitution.
Right. It's all based around restitution, restoring, right? The way we talked about repentance,
Right, making it right, fixing it, repairing the damage.
Which...
Right...
Like no amount of inflicting pain on Hitler,
like accounts for what Hitler did.
Yeah, it does not undo the Holocaust.
There's, yeah, there's no calculus there.
It doesn't repair anything.
Right.
And allow me to submit that his victims will either forgive him
or not would either forgive him or not forgive him.
But they wouldn't do it.
based on like, well, I can't forgive him until he's experienced 1,374 days of intense pain,
then I can forgive him.
Right? Well, this literally doesn't make sense.
Right? This is less sensible. This makes less sense than the church is teaching on the subject.
Right? So sometimes to get away from that,
Right? Because that's obviously super problematic and difficult and doesn't make a lot of sense.
And this is more, let's try to leave aside this caricature of Roman Catholic purgatory and move
more toward a caricature of Protestant, so Lafitte, again, a parody. Right? And as we were talking
about earlier in the episode, right, this move will...
from belief in content to feeling, right?
So the idea is that essentially, right, they reject God,
they don't believe in God, they don't accept God,
they don't want to worship God, they don't want to serve God.
And so they're sort of put into this hell
and tortured until they change their mind about that.
Yeah, one day after a thousand years of torture,
they're gonna be like, I think I made a huge mistake.
Yeah, okay.
find all worship God, right? Again, kind of super problematic.
Yeah, torturing people into changing their mind.
Yes, right. And if this is what God is going to do, that doesn't this justify like the
Spanish in acquisition.
Nobody justifies a Spanish.
acquisition. Should we go imitate God and go torture people and use the rule of law and use
everything we can to get them to accept Christ so they can have eternal life. Yeah, so that they
can maybe... I mean that's what God's going to do according to these folks. Yeah, so they can skip
it, skip the eternal, that not really eternal, that kind of... Yes, they should thank us.
This is the inquisitors idea of right this
This is the grand inquisitors' idea of God and evangelism, right?
Being promoted by the apocotostasis people whose raison d'etre is that they want to believe
in a kinder gentler God.
And now they've become the grand inquisitor, right?
These are those consequences we were talking about that are worse than the problem you're
trying to solve.
I love them even.
a little further and want to say, oh, tortured. We don't have any torture. Right? God said
this isn't inflicting suffering. It's just that's how they're experiencing God's love. God's
just loving on them so hard and they hate him. So they experience it as pain until they relent
and love him back.
So this is God is Glenn Close, right?
Like in fatal attraction.
This is God is Lenny and the open-minded men.
Like I don't...
Like...
Again.
Right?
These folks are gonna say this
and then say that the God taught
by the Apostolic teaching
preserved to the Orthodox Church is a monster.
Yeah.
for allowing people to choose eternal condemnation.
That makes him a monster.
But him aggressively loving people,
torturously, painfully until they relent and love him back. Oh, that's cool. That's good.
Yeah. And knowing full well that it hurts.
Yes. You know, knowing that it's torment.
So yeah.
Yeah.
just to cover another term.
Part of what happens, as I mentioned, is there's a lot of ways.
There's a lot of electrical fallacies that work here, right?
But one of the biggest ones is the construction of a false dilemma.
As I said, a lot of the argumentation is just negative argumentation
toward a straw man of a particular Western view of hell.
Yeah.
Right.
And therefore because that's all the argument the proponent of apocotostasis has, they
have to present the false dilemma of either you agree with me about apocotostasis in
subform, or you hold to this caricature view that I'm attacking.
Right?
There can be no other views, because if there are any other views, their whole argument
it falls apart because it's mostly negative arguments toward that.
that one particular caricature.
And what they call that caricature,
for those of you who have been fortunate enough,
not to be involved in any of these arguments,
is eternal conscious torment.
Yes, if you Google that exact phrase,
you will come up with 33,900 hits.
Right.
And so this is presented,
as this is the view of hell held by everyone
who doesn't believe in apocatostasis.
Right. And to show once again, we've already shown it, but quickly to show once again why
this doesn't work, right? You got three words, eternal conscious torment. What does eternal
mean here? Before you get into that, I wanted to say, by the way, since I decided to Google
up eternal conscious torment, like there is actually an essay on the gospel coalition website,
They are accepted.
Yeah, I mean, and this is not, like, I mean, I'm not a fan of the gospel coalition website,
just put that out there. But like, this is not just, this is not just pop theology.
This is, these are actually people who have do a little bit of theological work and have some,
you know, like this is theoretically some kind of mainstream Calvinism or whatever.
I don't know. It starts out this way. This is how the, the essay begins. Hell is a place of
eternal conscious torment for everyone who does not trust in Jesus Christ. Like, that's how it
starts up.
So like, you know, this is a real view that they're responding to.
Well, yeah, they tend to respond to caricatures of it, but also,
uh, never underestimate the, uh, ability of a Calvinist to wholeheartedly
believe in a caricature of his own position. Oh, sure.
Absolutely. That is, that is a Calvinist strat, argument strategy.
I've heard this many times, right? I have, I, literally,
I
know Calvinist professors with PhDs and theologians who if you try to say, well, that makes God the author
of evil. They just say, yes. So, right. Right. Or if you say, well, that makes human beings just robots.
They say like, yes. So, right. Exactly. Right. So I'm a feeling that's coming from it. Okay.
Okay.
Sure.
It turned out just torment.
But from the
perspective of right the orthodox view that we've been talking about has nothing to do with this.
What does eternal mean here? Does it mean like an unending series of moments in the sense that we
experience time now? Right? Like how does time work at the age to come? Yeah, I mean we have lots
of reasons to believe that that's not the way it works. Right. Right. We're talking about the age to come
Which is an age that has no end, yes.
But that is what it would experience time the same way.
So what do you mean by eternal? Right.
What does conscious mean here?
How does consciousness work at the age to come?
Yeah, and what about the whole weeping and gnashing thing?
Again, the madness.
So like, what kind of consciousness is that?
The loss of humanity.
Yeah.
Yeah. What does that mean in terms of consciousness?
What does torment mean here?
Tormat in the sense that it's unpleas-
tormented in the sense that God or someone else is actively torturing people? What do you mean by that?
Right? Because this isn't we in our second half repeated the biblical language about this.
So here's the images in scripture. Here's the language about this and this is how it gets picked up
in the Orthodox tradition. And this isn't the language.
The turtle conscious storm is
not the language that's used by the Scriptures, the fathers, or our tradition.
Yeah, and a lot of universalist critiques of eternal conscious torment will talk frequently
about the idea like, you know, well, you guys believe that God is torturing people forever,
but that's not what the Scripture actually says.
It does talk about being in torment forever, right?
We see that in Revelation in which that language is specifically applied to demons, but it
It doesn't say end-
God will torture them forever.
The only way you can connect those dots
is again using a Calvinist God.
Where literally everything that happens,
God has willed that thing to happen.
He's making it all happen.
So it's determinants.
Modernism.
God is the only one who really has activity,
that activity.
Yeah.
Everything else in the universe is passive before God.
Wait, yeah.
So again, Calvinism.
So yeah.
To an extent, to an extent, this whole argument between
apocodostasis and trochoccus torment is an intra-calvinist dispute.
It's the same presuppositions.
Right. It's the same, right? And that that's all it is, right?
And so where does the orthodox church stand on intra-calvinist disputes?
nowhere.
Right.
Let them do get out.
We don't share those presuppositions or shouldn't at least.
But so, right.
So are we saying that some significant number of people
are going to be condemned eternally?
No.
We don't know.
Right.
No.
Are we saying anyone in particular?
is going to be condemned eternally. Even Hitler.
No. Yeah, I think I think you might be able to make a decent argument for Judas.
As I recall some. Well, the Bible says Judas went to Hades, but even that,
see, we just imbiguated that. There you go. Yeah. Yeah.
Right? So we don't we don't know. And the fact that we don't know means it could be zero.
It could turn out in the end on the day of judgment that every human being is reconciled to
God.
Now, doesn't that contradict everything we've just said?
No.
If you think it does, you haven't been listening clearly.
Because the problem, what's condemned about apocodostasis is the idea of necessity and
inevitability.
Yeah, that is one person put it.
all shall be saved. Right. So we don't counter the idea that God is required to reconcile
everything to himself with the idea that God is required to not reconcile some things to
himself. Yeah. We counter it with the idea that God is completely free. Meaning God is free
to reconcile every human person to himself and grant the maternal life if he so
chooses. He is also free to send any of his creations to eternal condemnation. Right? God is free
to do these things. Right? So then why is it so important to condemn this idea of necessity?
Why does the idea of necessity make it a
And that's because of the consequences of believing that.
We've outlined some of those over the course of this episode, and especially this third half, but also the consequences to repentance.
two repentance.
It is critically important.
that we accept the teaching of scripture and the apostolic teaching is it's been preserved within
the Orthodox Church about the possibility of eternal condemnation for me, not for other people,
not for my enemies in quotation marks, right? Not for the people I don't like, not for the people I
I resent, right?
But for me, that I
have that possibility in my mind to drive me to repentance, meaning to drive me to
actually do things about repentance, right? To drive me to take my sin
seriously, to drive me to be ever more faithful to Christ, to drive me to pursue
Christ, right? So the way I've summarized this to the past is, universalism may end
up being true.
true in the sense that every person might be, but you can't be a universalist. It is a sin
to embrace the heresy of universalism, even if it turns out to be true. And again, this
is about yourself. We do not as orthodox Christians, and the church does not teach, that
You must accept that some particular-
person whom you loved is going to face eternal condemnation. Because the church
hasn't said that that person is under eternal condemnation, or will be
under eternal condemnation. Even being anathematized, even being condemned like
origin by an ecumenical counsel doesn't say that he is going to face eternal
condemnation. That judgment is up to Christ at the last judgment.
So you do not have to believe that just because the person you loved died outside of the
bounds of the Orthodox Church or Christianity broadly conceived or having committed some sin
that they didn't obviously repent of.
You are not required to believe that they are going to face eternal condemnation on the
last day.
In fact, you're called to pray for them.
Yeah, and what would be the point of praying for them if there was no hope for them?
Right if that's already sealed you're called to pray for them
Right, you called to intercede for them you called her as we talked about earlier they have to repent on their behalf
Right, this is the actual solution to that problem that the church gives us that doesn't have all those horrible follow-on consequences
The church gives us something to do
We offer memorials.
We offer memorial prayers. We gather together as a church and remember the people we lost or remember the people we love who are departed
Right, we pray for them to try to make things right
Right where they're not able to
We have these concrete things to do to
Work out those feelings and those fears and those doubts
Regarding those we love who have passed away
right
And just flipping the switch and saying, oh okay, I've got...
this intellectual argument where I don't need to worry about it anymore.
Assurance of other people's salvation that comes through apoconostasis.
Right?
Like crosses those wires.
Short circuits to the whole thing.
Because now I don't need to do any of those things.
Right?
So in this area, accept the recourse of...
the church has given you, the fix and the healing,
whether the church has given you,
rather than rejecting the church's teaching
and going after apple kind of sausage.
Yeah, so to summarize, I mean, there's a lot of things,
a lot of thoughts running around my head.
You know, at this point in my life,
I've been in a-
Orthodox Christian for 20, a little over 25 years.
And, but I remember immediately before I learned about the Orthodox faith and became Orthodox,
that I began to have a lot of questions about the faith in which I was raised.
And it was not because I encountered arguments against it.
Right, I didn't meet some
Apologists telling me that evangelical
Protestantism was wrong. It actually came out of the internal theology of that
movement. Certainly we were not universalists, right? But we definitely believed in
what is called eternal security, which is another variation in a lot of these
these things, which is sometimes summarized as once saved, always saved. It's a
kind of
You know, truncated version of one of those points
on the Calvinist tulip, perseverance of the saints.
And so, you know, I was raised with this idea
that once you get saved, which is an experience
of often praying a particular prayer to God,
repenting of your sins, asking him to be the Lord of your life
and you trust him forever for your salvation.
these kinds of things together.
And those of you who are familiar with this tradition, you probably recognize that combination
that once that happens for you, then you have effectively your ticket to heaven.
You've got it.
You can't lose it, no matter what you do.
Right?
Now it was generally also believed that if you really did have it, that there would be
effects in your life that you wouldn't live any of a life.
that the worst that can happen to you is that you would become and I always love this word. This is very common in Baptist circles back slidden
You know still saved with backslidden. In other words, you're a Christian. You got your ticket to heaven
But you're not living right
Well one of the questions that I began to have in my late teens early 20s
was
Okay, if I really do have my my cell.
kind of wrapped up. If it's taken care of, if assurance of salvation means absolute mathematical
certainty of salvation guaranteed, right? Then what am I doing in church? What am I actually
accomplishing here? You know, also why should I behave according to moral strictures? Like why? Because
You know, it's not because I just suddenly had this inner impulse, like, I want to do evil things.
I want to taste the wild side. You know, but, but, uh, for instance, the job that I worked, um, I was paid by the
hour. So it was often, uh, the case that I would get offered work on Sunday mornings.
And since I wasn't making a lot of money, um, there was good reason to work on Sunday morning.
And if I didn't believe that participation in
corporate worship actually had any critical effect in my Christian life, then why did I
need to prioritize it such that I would do things like make less money? You know, especially
at a time of my life when I really could use the money. And so since I didn't have a good
response to that question, I began to take some work on Sunday mornings. And I was on church
other Sunday mornings, but I didn't just like sit home.
But it seemed like a pretty decent balance.
I was like, oh, well, I'll work sometimes.
And certainly, someone's in college, I was in my early 20s.
There are definitely moral temptations.
There are definitely things that I wanted to do.
I didn't really see the harm in them, but I would have been told that they were wrong.
And so I was like, but I got my salvation nailed down.
Why?
If I just, you know, if I do it this one time or...
whatever you've had a pattern of doing it, there's no actual risk.
So part of the reason that I became Orthodox, one of the motivations that I had was because
of this question of like, well, what am I supposed to be doing as a Christian? Is there something
to do? Is something more than just recruit more Christians? Which again, I could just ignore if I
wanted to, not absolutely required. Is there something more to do?
And then I encountered the Orthodox Church
and encountered the teaching that life is supposed
to be about repentance, that the whole life
is for repentance.
And this was utterly revolutionary for me,
utterly revolutionary,
because it made everything that I did critical.
It made everything that I did important.
It made everything that I did have an ultimate effect
of permanent importance, right?
It did not mean that all of my history, other than that one moment of getting on my knees
and praying when I was six years old in front of my bed, that all the rest of that history
didn't matter.
It meant that it all mattered, that it's all going to be carried with me into eternity,
that it all becomes permanent.
And the whole shape of my life is what will be carried forward.
consequence of
of universalism is that it doesn't matter.
No matter what version you want to put on it,
whether it's the, well, it matters temporarily,
but not long-term, it still ultimately doesn't matter.
That's why some critics of universalism have said
that it's the erasure of history,
because it is, right?
St. Piusius famously said, don't believe those who say that all will be saved because
it means that we won't struggle.
I mean, that's pretty straightforward.
Because if there is nothing at risk, if eternal condemnation is not a possibility, then
the fire that's going to be lit under a Christian is just simply not there.
Now someone might argue, well shouldn't you...
a better reason to struggle than just being afraid of being punished. Well, again, we talked
about all of that, right? The point is that there is something at risk. There is something
at risk. Another one of the modern Holy Fathers of the Church, Saint Siddling on the
Athenite, I just saw this again recently. I was reminded of this. He said, this, understand
two thoughts and fear them. One says you are a saint.
The other you won't be saved. Both of these thoughts are from the enemy and there's no truth in them.
But think this way, I am a great sinner, but the Lord is merciful. He loves people very much and he will forgive my sins.
If you eliminate one side of that, right, then you're eliminating the whole Christian life.
Repentance ultimately does not matter.
It's optional.
Like it's a boom.
even for the people who say that, you know, hell is a kind of purgatory
experience that will eventually go away.
Repent, it's like, well, you can repent now or you can repent in the next life.
Yeah, why shouldn't I wait? Why shouldn't I? I could have both. I could have my
I can eat it too.
You know?
So, universalism like the cow...
the Calvinist arguments on which it depends, it eliminates the very character of repentance.
And repentance is to change to become more like our Lord Jesus Christ.
Right?
It's to become more like our Lord Jesus Christ.
It's not, as we said, it's not about feeling a certain feeling or feeling bad, guilty,
or whatever, regretful.
It's about becoming more like our Lord Jesus Christ.
And so being saved.
is to become like Christ.
Right?
So you can't be saved without repentance.
That's like saying, I want to get wet without any water.
It's not a thing.
You can't get wet without water.
You can't be saved without repentance,
because repentance is the process of being saved.
Salvation is not a status that you receive at the end.
It is becoming more like Christ.
It is this elevation to become as Lord says equal to the angels.
.
Right?
So, you know, as Father Stephen said, we don't know, we don't know how many or if any actually
will be eternally condemned.
And God forbid, like I find it really reprehensible sometimes when certain people say that if you
believe in eternal condemnation as it's laid out in the scripture and church fathers and
so forth, that means you like the idea of being people suffering.
Use me. False. Utterly false. Right?
The fact that I believe that frightening things are true does not mean I want them to be true.
Right? Something is true whether or not I want it to be true. That's part of why it's true.
You know. But the whole Christian life, it's not that it's about trying to avoid eternal
condemnation, right? But that is one of the things that's
included.
in the broad, comprehensive, complicated, and endlessly fascinating image that the scriptures and the whole Orthodox tradition present
in order for us to fix our eyes on Christ and to press forward to the prize of the High Calling of God as the Apostle Paul said.
Maybe you don't need to think about eternal condemnation in order.
to do that. But you know, some of the saints who are the holiest people, like the holiest
people who really knew God and really loved Him, that was part of their toolkit of salvation.
If St. Pius uses that as part of his toolkit of salvation, then who am I to think that
I don't need that.
You know, I'm nobody.
I'm nothing like him in terms of...
sanctity. And so if he needs it, then how much more do I need it? And it's not because
I want to dwell on darkness and gnashing of teeth and like a fire or whatever. But it's
I need to know that there's this boundary that exists there. There's a boundary. And
unless I keep vigilant, I could be potentially tossed over it.
So, everything I'm about to say is once again, aimed not at good people who are drawn toward
some kind of view of apocodostasis for emotional reasons.
I have love for a departed loved one.
kind of thing. There are a lot of people, as we've said several times, who are drawn to
it because of that, and honestly, and while we've argued that's a bad solution, what I'm
about to say is directed at the other group, because there is this other group that finds
attractive I think for other reasons.
What these folks have in common is a certain class identity to be blunt.
Right?
We're talking about upper middle class intellectuals, college professors, other people in the professional
managerial class.
There's a reason it's referred to as liberal theology.
And it's not just that like, oh, those people are libs and therefore they believe liberal
theology.
it's much deep
than that. Right. So liberalism proper, uh, brings about and grows through the bourgeois
revolutions of the 18th and 19th centuries, right, where starting in the US and France,
the mercantile class seized political power through violence from the feudal nobility. The
King the lords.
who had previously possessed political power,
the newly expanding Burkin tile class,
had money, they seized political power through revolution.
They became the new governors and rulers of the territory.
And with their newfound political power,
were not per se inclined to the same sense
of obligation before God that their feudal predecessors had been.
because in addition to not accepting the hierarchical ordering of the world in feudal monarchy,
they also didn't accept the hierarchical ordering of the world religiously within the church.
This is why the French Revolution, they go after the Roman Catholic Church.
This is why Roman Catholicism was so very unpopular throughout US history.
orthodoxy too, by the way, though too illessory.
because we were a smaller presence.
But go look at the history of the Greek community
in Toronto and Canada, for example,
so how they face the same kinds of persecutions
that Roman Catholics did in the United States.
That was sort of rejected.
And so that class of people wanted authority
not only in the realm of politics,
but also in the realm of religion.
And so you
get the creation, for example, of the United States in the colonial period of a pastorate that is
in parallel with this mercantile class. You have lawyers, you have physicians, you have pastors
and Parsons, right? And these are the influencers of society. And again, because they now
Now, receive this religious authority to one.
might expect that in the same way a feudal Lord had certain obligations that they viewed
as imposed by God on them morally toward the peasants who worked their lands. Right? You
might expect that the new sort of nobility might feel those same obligations or that because
they now had this religious authority, they might feel the same obligations that bishops
did to carefully
poor and those who are under their authority. And frankly, the whole current of philosophy
and theology at the time ran in the opposite direction.
Ran in the direction of justifying why there is no such responsibility.
Why the person who has worked hard and earned his position of power and authority has no obligation
into those beneath.
him in terms of the class structure because those people are beneath him because they are
reprobate, they are less virtuous and if they are virtuous, they will inevitably arrive at their
own station. This is just a constant current in intellectual history. This grasping of universalism
Bye!
this university intellectual class among the upper middle and lower upper class in the
United States and Europe is part and parcel of this, right? Because what ultimate function
does it have for them? Right? We talked about the other group of people where this is functioning
to give them consolation in the face of someone they've lost. For these other people, for
these are
intellectuals. This is doing something different. This is justifying them not caring about the poor.
This is justifying them not caring or doing anything about injustice in the world.
This is serving the function of justifying them doing nothing to try to evangelize anyone.
This is used to justify them not having any responsibility.
to investigate their own religious beliefs very deeply and definitely never had to make
it a sharp distinctions that might make things awkward in a dinner party.
This is functionally a sort of neo-ferrous aism.
is a belief used to justify oneself.
To identify oneself.
as one of the open-minded, one of the elite, to represent, I am above those sort of lower-class
pearls who believe in things like hell, who believe all of these fables. And believing in Plato's
God helps them a lot because Plato's God is a God of aristocratic rationalism.
So
And I'm not just saying this as an attack on them.
I'm saying this because in the same way
that we say to those folks who have grasped onto this
because they need it for consolation,
the church provides you with the means of having consolation
that doesn't come with all the costs associated with,
with latching onto this deviant view, apoconostosis.
Right.
In the same way we need to
because we love our brothers and sisters,
from that other group, from that intellectual group,
right, from that upper class group.
We love them too,
and that means we need to call them
to repentance and faith too.
We need to call on them to see,
see trying to justify themselves,
see trying to justify the way of life
they've become addicted to.
Uh, call on them to get rid of the false idol of their own self perception.
As one of the elite, one of the knowledgeable, one of the intelligent,
to abandon those things and come and come to repentance.
So there are going to be a bunch of people who listen to what I said in the third half,
and say, oh, there he is a hater. He is a D.B.H. hater. He hates.
David Bentley, he hates these people.
I do not.
I want David Bentley heart to repent and draw close to Christ.
I want him to repent of a lot of the things he's set.
Meaning I want him to sort of repair the damage.
I want him to draw closer to Christ.
I want him to live a Christian life.
I want him to become a saint.
That's what I want.
But that means right now...
With what he's doing now and teaching now and promoting now, I have to oppose him.
And this is the truth for us all the time in our Christian lives.
Because it's not just those folks who are addicted to a certain way of life and did not
having things be awkward and not having to make our distinctions.
It's all of us to one degree or another.
There's a small group of us who are like super combative and aggressive.
I say-
because I'm probably one of those people who need to reign it in a little, right? But most of us
don't like conflict, don't like having to take, take stance, don't like having to oppose someone,
especially don't like having to oppose someone to their face, right? But often, not just sometimes,
but often that's exactly what we have
to do if we love someone. We have to tell them they're wrong, that they're deeply wrong,
that they're wrong for bad reasons. And that what they're doing is going to be self-destructive.
It would be great to honestly believe that everybody can just do anything they want. And
all turn out great.
the end for them and everyone else. I mean, that's kind of ridiculous because some of the things they
want to do would be directly hurting other people. But that's not reality. That's not the real world.
That's like a child's view of the world. Everybody just goes off and follows their bliss.
right? In the real world we need to work together to sort these things out and find salvation and part of that.
part of that means that we need to have some uncomfortable clashes. We need to have
some uncomfortable discussions. We need to hash some things out. We need to risk
hurting feelings. So that in the end, everybody, myself included, right? I need people
to challenge me often. So whether or not I'm married, my wife is good at it. She
calls almost everything I say into question.
But we all need that to find salvation
and to find eternal life.
And our goal has to be what God wills,
which is that all men should be saved
and come to the knowledge of the truth.
Amen.
Well, that is our show for tonight.
Next time I think should be our third anniversary show.
That'll be fun.
Thank you very much for listening everyone.
We'd like to hear from you. You can email us at LordofSpirit.nationfaith.com.
You can send us a message or a Facebook page.
You can leave us a voice mail at speakpipe.com slash Lordofspirit.
And join us for our live broadcast on the second fourth Thursday of the month at 7 p.m.
Eastern 4 p.m. Pacific.
No stop signs or speed limit.
Nothing's going to slow me down.
And if you are on Facebook, unlike Father Stephen,
who actually lurks through his wife's account.
You can follow our page.
You can also join our discussion.
You can leave reviews and ratings everywhere, but most importantly, share this show with a friend,
and you know it's going to love it. And even those who will hate this and to it.
And finally, be sure to go to www.hankshephate.com.saucesupport and help make sure we and lots of
other AFR podcasters stay on the air. Like a wheel, to the spin it. Nobody's gonna mess me around.
Thank you, good night, and may God bless you all.
You've been listening to The Lord of Spirits with Orthodox Christian priests,
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father
Stephen DeYoung, a listener-supported presentation of ancient faith radio.
And I beheld and I heard the voice of many angels round about the throne and the beasts
and the elders, and the number of them was 10,000 times 10,000 and thousands of thousands
saying with a loud voice worthy is the land that was slain to receive power and riches
and wisdom and strength and honor and glory and blessing.
Revelation.
But one thing is needed, and Mary has chosen that good part, which will not be taken away from her.